Homage to the Buddha Shakyamuni.
Nam mô Phật Bổn Sư Thích Ca Mâu Ni. À
Greetings, esteemed fellow practitioners.  Dear
kính chào các quý đạo hữu. Kính thưa các
fellow practitioners, we continue with
quý đạo hữu, chúng ta lại tiếp tục với
the topic of cultivating the Bodhi mind.
chủ đề về phát tâm bồ đề
Let's share together about
chúng ta a cùng à chia sẻ với nhau về
the Bodhi mind cultivation of
cái việc phát tâm bồ đề của Thiện Tài
Sudhana.
Đồng Tử.
Regarding the first part of the story about the Bodhisattva Sudhana's aspiration, we
về cái việc phát tâm của Thiện Tài Đồng
discussed the need for
Tử phần một thì đã nói về việc mà cần
single-minded devotion to the Bodhisattva path.
phải nhất tâm cần cầu phát tâm bồ đề
Sudhana obeyed the teachings
thì ngài Thiện Tài Đồng Tử đã vâng lời
of
của
Manjushri and wholeheartedly
ngài Văn Thù Sư Lợi phát tâm nhất tâm
aspired to supreme enlightenment. Now, let's
cần cầu vô thượng bồ đề rồi
continue to see what
để chúng ta tiếp tục xem là ngài Văn Thù
Manjushri further taught Sudhana about
Sư Lợi tiếp tục dạy
what to do
À Thiện Tài Đồng Tử những gì nên làm gì
after
sau khi mà
sincerely and
chân thật
wholeheartedly aspiring to the
rồi nhất tâm
Bodhisattva path. Today,
cần cầu phát tâm bồ đề thì hôm nay chúng
we move on to the second part, "Sudhana's Aspiration for Bodhisattva Path," titled "The Practice of Close
ta vào bài số hai là Thiện Tài Đồng Tử
Interaction."
với tựa đề Hạnh thân cận.
Learning and obeying virtuous teachers
Học hỏi vâng thuận bậc thiện tri thức
is an excerpt from the Avatamsaka Sutra, Chapter
được trích soạn từ kinh Hoa Nghiêm phẩm
39, Entering the Dharma Realm.  Now, I invite all of you to
39 nhập pháp giới. Thì giờ này thỉnh các
join hands and recite the Buddha's name, and
quý đạo hữu chúng ta chắp tay niệm Phật
then we will begin reading the scriptures.
rồi chúng ta vào văn kinh.
We recite the Buddha's name primarily to express
Chúng ta niệm Phật để thứ nhất là hướng
our gratitude to the Buddha and to pray for his blessings
tâm tới tri ân Phật và cầu Phật gia hội
in all aspects of
cho chúng ta trong tất cả mọi sự
our lives, so that we may always strive to cultivate ourselves and
của chúng ta để chúng ta luôn luôn hướng
seek supreme enlightenment.
Phật mà tu tập mà cầu vô thượng bồ đề.
Namo
Nam a mô
Buddha, the original teacher
Phật à bổn
Shakyamuni Buddha.
Thích Ca
Namo
Nam A
Buddha, the original teacher
Phật à bổn sư
Shakyamuni Buddha.
Thích Ca
[Laughter]
[Tiếng cười]
Namo Buddha, the original teacher
Nam mô Phật à bổn sư
Shakyamuni Buddha. The
Thích Ca Mâu Ni
scripture is as follows.  At that time, Manjushri Bodhisattva, the
Văn kinh như sau. Lúc đó Văn Thù Sư Lợi
Elephant King, turned to look at the young boy
Bồ Tát Như Tượng Vương xoay nhìn Thiện
Sudhana and said, "Excellent,
Tài Đồng Tử mà bảo rằng: "Lành thay,
excellent, good boy! You have
lành thay này thiện nam tử, ngươi đã
made the vow of supreme enlightenment, and you wish to
phát tâm vô thượng bồ đề, lại muốn thân
associate with virtuous teachers to inquire about the
cận các bực thiện tri thức để hỏi Bồ Tát
Bodhisattva practice and cultivate the Bodhisattva path."
hạnh, tu Bồ Tát đạo."
So, dear fellow practitioners, here we are discussing the story of
Thì kính thưa quý đạo hữu, ở đây là sau
Sudhana, who, following the instructions of Manjushri,
lời ngài Văn Thù Sư Lợi
wholeheartedly aspired to attain supreme enlightenment
nhất tâm cần cầu phát tâm vô thượng bồ
.  Then he asked, "
đề. Xong rồi thì ngài lại hỏi rằng là
Now that you have made the Bodhisattva vow, how should you practice the Bodhisattva path
giờ đã phát tâm Bồ Đề rồi thì tu Bồ Tát
?"  How does one practice the Bodhisattva path
hạnh như thế nào? Tu Bồ Tát đạo như thế
?  Then, Manjushri Bodhisattva
nào? thì ngài Văn Thù Sư Lợi mới tán
praised Sudhana, saying that he had already aspired to
thán Thiện Tài Đồng Tử là đã phát tâm vô
supreme enlightenment and yet still
thượng bồ đề rồi lại còn à
wished to associate with virtuous teachers to
muốn thân cận các bậc thiện tri thức để
inquire about the practice of Bodhisattva conduct and the Bodhisattva path.  So
hỏi Bồ Tát hạnh tu Bồ Tát đạo. Tức là
why is it said that we are asking about the Bodhisattva's practice and the
tại sao lại nói là hỏi Bồ Tát hạnh tu Bồ
Bodhisattva path?  In other words, the question is:
Tát đạo? Tức là hỏi là Bồ Tát thì có
what virtues should a Bodhisattva cultivate?  As for practicing the Bodhisattva path,
những hạnh gì cần tu. Còn tu Bồ Tát đạo
that is, how should one practice to
tức là cái hạnh đấy thì tu thế nào để
achieve that practice?  Therefore, it is called
thành tựu được cái hạnh đấy. Cho nên gọi
inquiring about Bodhisattva conduct and cultivating the Bodhisattva path.
là hỏi Bồ Tát hạnh, tu Bồ Tát đạo. Hỏi
Ask what kind of virtues need to be cultivated,
xem cái hạnh này cần phải phải tu cái
and what the path to enlightenment is, and
hạnh gì và đạo là con đường không mà
how to cultivate it, what to cultivate, and how to practice it
cách tu thế nào, tu cái gì và cách tu
.  This young boy, Sudhana, is
thế nào? Ngài Thiện Tài Đồng Tử này hay
excellent.  Whatever you ask, you will practice that.  That
lắm. Cứ hỏi cái gì là sẽ tu cái đấy. Rất
's great.  With a calm and focused mind, please continue reading the
là hay. Tâm chế quán xin đọc tiếp văn
scripture.
kinh.
O virtuous man, associating with and offering gifts to
này thiện nam tử, thân cận cúng dường
virtuous teachers is the
các bậc thiện tri thức là nhân duyên
first and foremost condition for attaining the fullness of
trước nhất để được đầy đủ nhất thiết
omniscience.  Therefore, you should not tire of this work
trí. Vì thế nên công việc này ngươi chớ
.
có mỏi nhàm.
Do we see here that giving is the foremost of the six paramitas?  The six perfections
trong lục độ ba la mật không? Lục độ ba
are generosity, morality, diligence,
la mật là bố thí trì giới tinh tấn nhẫn
patience, and meditation.  Here, Manjushri
nhục thiền định. Thì ở đây ngài Văn Thù
Bodhisattva says that associating with and offering gifts to
Sư Lợi ngài nói rằng thân cận cúng dường
virtuous teachers is the
các bậc thiện tri thức là nhân duyên
primary condition for attaining complete
trước nhất để được đầy đủ nhất thiết
omniscience.  That is to say, in practicing the Bodhisattva path,
trí. Tức là chúng ta tu hành Bồ Tát đạo
we must strive for ultimate fulfillment.  The ultimate
chúng ta phải cầu nhất thiết chí. Nhất
truth is wisdom that sees and knows everything.  With utmost
thiết chí là trí tuệ thấy biết hết. nhất
concentration, one can
thiết chí
see and know the truth, see and know the ultimate
thấy biết được chân thật, thấy biết được
truth, see and know everything, and know that there is
khết, thấy biết cùng khắp, thấy biết
nothing one does not know.  To achieve
không gì không biết. Mà muốn được như
that, we must associate with virtuous and knowledgeable people
thế thì chúng ta phải thân cận bậc thiện
.  But the intention was to get close enough
hữu tri thức. Nhưng mà với cái ý định là
to make offerings first.  That's the
thân cận để cúng dường đã. Đấy, với cái
kind of selfless attitude one needs to learn.  So,
tâm xả như thế mới học được. Đấy,
has anyone here seen the TV series Journey to
thì ở đây đã ai xem cái bộ phim mà
the West?
Tây Du Ký không?
This Journey to the West movie is really good.
Cái bộ phim Tây Du Ký này rất là hay.
Perhaps Wu Cheng'an, being
Có lẽ là ông Ngô Thừa Ân này ông cũng là
a Buddhist himself, was
một cái người học Phật cho nên ông cũng
deeply imbued with Buddhist teachings, which is why
thấm nhuần cái giáo lý nhà Phật cho nên
he made this film so
ông ấy làm ra cái bộ phim này rất là
well.  In that final scene, when
hay. Thì ở cái cảnh cuối cùng ấy mà thầy
Tang Sanzang and his disciples go to retrieve the scriptures, they
trò Đường Tăng đi lấy đi lấy kinh ấ thế
simply ask the Buddha for the scriptures
rồi đến đấy là chỉ bạch Phật xin kinh
.  When people asked the Buddha for scriptures, the Buddha
thôi. Gặp Đức Phật xin kinh thì Đức Phật
told them to go to the place where the two men
có nói là vào trong chỗ hai cái ông mà
guarded the scripture repository. The
ông ấy gác cái kho kinh ấy, kinh sách
men who arranged the scriptures would give them to the scriptures, and then they could
các ông là ông xếp cho kinh sách rồi thì
go home.  The monk obtained the scriptures and then
đi về. Thầy trọ là có được kinh sách rồi
went home.  On the way back, they encountered a storm.
đi về. đi về thì gặp phải một cơn bão.
So he threw those sacred books
Thế là nó mới làm tung chỗ sách kinh ấy
into the sea.  And then,
xuống xuống biển. Thế rồi thì đến lúc
what were they going to do with the money when they finally pulled it out?  Take them out and dry them in the sun.  It
mới vớt lên để gì? Vớt lên để phơi. Thì
turns out that the scriptures contain no words, absolutely no
hóa ra trong kinh không có chữ, chả có
meaning whatsoever.
chữ nghĩa gì.
As teacher and student, we must return to the present.  When you go back, you'll
là thầy trò là phải quay lại. Quay lại
see those two guys, and he'll ask for
thì đến gặp hai cái ông đấy, ông ấy xin
the last bowl.  The bowl, the
nốt cái bát đấy. Cái bát mà cái bình bát
alms bowl, that the Tang Monk and his disciples
mà đi khất thực mà thầy trò Đường Tăng
had to use to beg for
phải đi khất thực bằng cái bình bát để
food.  Then the two guards at the
ăn ấy. Thì đến là hai cái ông gác ở cái
warehouse asked for the last bowl.  Then
kho đấy là ông ấy xin nốt cái bát. Thì
Sun Wukong was indignant and said that even in the presence of
Tôn Ngự Không là bất bình lại bảo ở chỗ
Buddha, it still felt like
Phật rồi mà vẫn còn giống như kiểu là
bribery.  Then Master Tang
đút lót ấy. Thế thì thầy Đường Tăng thì
said, "Just give it to me, just give me
thầy mới bảo là thôi cho đi, thôi cho
that alms bowl so I can go get the scriptures."
cái bình bát ấy đi để mà còn lấy kinh.
Then, after giving them
Thế thì rồi thì cho rồi thì bắt đầu là
away, he started arranging them, and he arranged the scriptures that had text on them.
xếp ra thì ông xếp cho các kinh có chữ.
That's what makes it so meaningful here.  If
Đấy thì ở đây nó rất là ý nghĩa. Nếu
we come to Buddhism but do not
chúng ta đến với Phật mà lại không tu để
practice to cultivate and let go of our attachments,
tập để xả các cái tâm đi.
So, what do we still have left?  The teacher and student
Tức là chúng ta vẫn còn cái gì? Thầy trò
still have the alms bowl, which means they are still
vẫn còn cái bình bát, tức là vẫn còn
thinking about eating, thinking about this body.
nghĩ đến việc ăn, nghĩ đến cái thân này.
What is eating?  It's for making a living.  As long as one still thinks
Ăn là gì? Là để nuôi thân. Vẫn còn nghĩ
of this physical body as not yet enlightened,
đến là cái thân này thì nó chưa giác ngộ
and still clings to the mind, then one is
mà vẫn còn cái tâm thủ chấp ấ thì nó
not enlightened, not liberated, and therefore cannot
không không giác ngộ chưa giải thoát làm
have the scriptures.  That scripture is just a symbol of
sao có kinh. Kinh đấy là biểu tượng cho
enlightenment, not the
sự giác ngộ thôi mà chứ không phải cái
bag containing the scriptures.  That's just in the movie to make it
túi kinh đâu. Đấy là trong phim cho
easier for people to understand, but in reality, going to
người ta dễ hiểu thôi chứ thực ra là đi
get the scriptures means going there to practice and attain
lấy kinh là đi sang đấy đã được tu tập
enlightenment.  But what if
cho nó giác ngộ đấy. Thế nhưng mà nếu
you're still being stubborn about even something as simple as
như mà anh mà còn thủ chấp dù chỉ là một
food?
cái vấn đề ăn uống thôi.
The alms bowl symbolizes the act
Cái bình bát là biểu tượng cho cái việc
of taking food, and you only need a little bit
mà lấy đồ để ăn mà anh chỉ cần một chút
to eat.  He cannot attain
về ăn thôi. Anh không thể đạt giải thoát
liberation, he cannot attain enlightenment.
được, không thể đạt giác ngộ được. Cho
Therefore, you must let go of
nên là cái đó là anh phải xả thết tham,
greed, let go of the attachment to
xả biết ái nào là yêu thích cái bình bát
that alms bowl.  By letting go of all greed and attachment, one will attain
ấy đi. Xả hết tham ái thì sẽ được giác
enlightenment.  So, at that time, the scripture had writing on it, meaning
ngộ. Thì lúc đó kinh là có chữ tức là có
what did it contain?  With enlightenment comes liberation.  So
gì? Có giác ngộ, có giải thoát. Nên
we need to understand that meaning.
chúng ta phải hiểu cái ý nghĩa đó. Thì ở
This is similar to the idea of ​​an
đây thì cũng tương đồng với cái ý mà của
enlightened person.  So, what do we have to do first
người giác ngộ thôi. Thì đầu tiên là ta
?  Why should we practice associating closely with
phải gì? Phải thực hành thân cận bậc
virtuous and knowledgeable people?  For offerings
thiện hữu tri thức là để gì? Để cúng
.  To make offerings to virtuous and knowledgeable friends
dường. Để cúng dường các bậc thiện hữu
.  Although those masters don't need it, is
tri thức. Tuy rằng các bậc ấy không cần
n't that a form of spiritual practice?  So,
nhưng cái đó là pháp tu phải không? Thì
when we approach virtuous and knowledgeable people
khi chúng ta đến các bậc thiện hữu tri
, we make offerings to them, and
thức, chúng ta cúng dường cho các vị
then these
thiện hữu tri thức rồi rồi chúng ta các
virtuous and knowledgeable people will teach
bậc thiện hữu tri thức sẽ dạy cho chúng
us how to make offerings. It's not that
ta đi cúng dường chứ không phải là chúng
we have to make offerings to them first
ta phải cúng dường cho các ngài, các
before they teach us.  If our hearts are
ngài mới dạy chúng ta đâu. Mà tâm chúng
stingy and greedy, we cannot find
ta mà keo rít thì không thể tìm đến được
virtuous friends who can teach
các bậc thiện hữu tri thức dạy cho chúng
us the path to liberation.  It's a matter of cause and effect.
ta pháp giải thoát. Đó là nhân và duyên.
Is that right?  If our hearts are ungrateful,
Có phải không? Tâm chúng ta vô ơn thì
how can we find a place
làm sao mà chúng ta đi tìm được cái chỗ
where we can learn something good?  Since all
nào học được tốt đẹp? Thì nhất thiết
phenomena are created by the mind, if
pháp giới duy tâm tạo mà tâm chúng ta
our minds are stingy and ungrateful, then we will
keo rít, tâm chúng ta vô ơn thì chúng ta
only engage in exploitative and harmful actions
chỉ đi làm các cái việc lợi dụng và ác
.  We're going to drift away from those wise and
hại thôi. Chúng ta sẽ rời xa các bậc
virtuous friends, aren't we?  Even if one cannot
thiện hữu tri thức đấy phải không? Không
learn the highest and most virtuous teachings,
học được các cái pháp cao tốt vì thiện
what kind of practice must one cultivate?  People
pháp gì? Cái pháp bố thí rồi người ta
only teach us the practice of giving after we have already learned about giving.  Is
mới dạy cho mình cái pháp bố thí. Có
that right?  If your heart is still filled with resentment,
phải không? Thế nếu tâm mình còn keo rít
how can you understand what others are teaching? You
người ta dạy làm sao mà mình hiểu được
won't understand, and you might even get annoyed and
không hiểu được mà thậm chí mình bực
leave.  Therefore,
mình mình bỏ đi nữa. Thế cho nên ở đây
this is what Manjushri taught here.  This
ngài Văn Thù Sư Lợi dạy thế này. Này
virtuous man's close association and offerings to
thiện nam tử thân cận cúng dường các bực
virtuous teachers is the primary condition
thiện tri thức là nhân duyên trước nhất
for attaining the fullness of omniscience.  That's
để được đầy đủ nhất thiết trí. Đấy là
just the initial connection.  Therefore,
nhân duyên trước nhất thôi. Vì thế công
you should not tire of this work.
việc này ngươi chớ có mỏi nhàm. Cái lời
This teaching is something that, if you do
dạy này là lời dạy
n't remember it, you can't practice it
phải nói là không ghi nhớ thì không tu
.  Because those who practice the Bodhisattva path
được. Bởi vì người tu hành Bồ Tát đạo
must always be learning,
này phải luôn luôn học hỏi, không bao
never considering that learning to be enough.  One must
giờ cho việc học đấy là đủ. Phải luôn
always practice what has been taught
luôn thực hành những lời đã được dạy
and never think that
và không bao giờ được nghĩ rằng thực
practicing is enough; only achieving
hành như thế đã là đủ mà phải thành tựu
supreme enlightenment is sufficient.  If
vô thượng bồ đề mới là đủ. Chứ nếu bây
we haven't achieved anything yet, and
giờ chúng ta chưa thành tựu, chúng ta đi
we consider ourselves to have reached our goal as sufficient,
đến đây, chúng ta đã coi nó là đủ rồi
then how will we ever get to our destination?  It's just
thì chúng ta làm gì đến được đích. Nó
like that road.  We are
cũng giống như con đường đi ấy. Chúng ta
going from here to our destination, which is
đi từ đây đáng nhẽ đến đích là đi từ đây
500 meters from here to that other location.
đến địa điểm kia cách nhau là 500 m.
But we've only gone one meter, and we've
Nhưng chúng ta đi được 1 m, chúng ta đã
already said that's enough, so how can we go any further?
bảo đủ rồi thì làm sao mà đi được nữa,
How can we get there?  Is that right?
làm sao mà đến nơi? Có phải không? Cho
Therefore, our practice should aim to
nên cái việc tu tập của chúng ta là phải
achieve supreme enlightenment.  But to
đến thành tựu vô thượng bồ đề. Mà muốn
achieve supreme enlightenment, we
thành tựu vô thượng bồ đề thì chúng ta
must learn from virtuous and knowledgeable people,
phải đến các bậc thiện hữu tri thức học
right?   There
phải không?
are so many wise and
học thì rất là nhiều các bậc thiện trị
virtuous people in our lives
hữu tri thức trong các cuộc đời nhiều
that we are bound to meet them all, and understand
như vậy thì chúng ta đều phải gặp, đều
why.  Everyone has to study.
phải gì? Đều phải học.
So, if we don't study but
Thế nếu chúng ta không học mà chúng ta
feel we have learned, then the Bodhi mind will
cảm thấy học được rồi thì tâm bồ đề sẽ
wither.  Is that right?  No, this cannot
thối. Có phải không? Không không tiếp
continue.  So this is what we need to
tục được. Cho nên ở đây là việc chúng ta
emphasize.
nhấn mạnh nhá.
Making close contact with and offering gifts to virtuous teachers
Thân cận cúng dường các bậc thiện tri
is the first and foremost condition for attaining the
thức là nhân duyên trước nhất để được
fullness of omniscience.  Therefore,
đầy đủ nhất thiết trí. Vì thế nên công
you should not tire of this work; you
việc này ngươi chớ có nhà mỏi thì mình
must make a vow that for all eternity you will
phải phát nguyện là đời đời kiếp kiếp
seek to be close to virtuous and knowledgeable people, and receive offerings so
con xin thân cận bậc thiện hữu tri thức
that you may learn and practice without tire of it.  I
cúng dường để học tu không nhà mỏi. Mình
had to make that vow, otherwise
phải phát nguyện như thế đấy chứ không
I would get bored.  The Mind-Illuminating Contemplation remembers
thì mình sẽ chán. Tâm chiếu hản quán nhớ
that in this lifetime of the Mind-Illuminating Contemplation
là trong cái kiếp này của Tâm Chiếu Hàn
, the Mind-Illuminating Contemplation has already told the esteemed
Quán ấy, Tâm Chiếu Ân Quán đã kể cho các
Dharma friends in many
quý đạo hữu trong rất là nhiều buổi
Dharma discourses that I humbly ask the Buddha for nothing
trạch pháp rồi đấy là con bạch Phật con
.  So, I made a
không cầu bất cứ một cái gì. Đấy, có lời
vow that I wouldn't ask for anything at all.
phát nguyện con không cầu bất cứ một gì.
Right now, my child's life is in danger of
Hiện tại đời sống của con là có thể dung
something
sắc của con sẽ bị một cái gì đó cho nó
ruining their appearance.  Then all the possessions were lost, the
hủy hoại đi. Rồi thì tài sản mất hết,
family was torn apart, and everything was gone.  I
gia đình chia lìa tất cả mất hết. Con
only pray that I may find a teacher who
chỉ cầu con có được một người thầy mà ở
will guide me so that I may achieve success in my
nơi người thầy sẽ dạy cho con để con
spiritual practice.  So, does that
thành tựu được cái việc tu tập thôi. Đấy
mean that when my heart makes
thì có phải là tâm mình phát nguyện cầu
such a vow, there are no obstacles
như thế là nó không có chướng ngại
?  What's there to be embarrassed about?  That's why
không? Có gì chữa ngại. Thế cho nên ở
this is called seeking out virtuous and knowledgeable people
đây gọi là đi cầu bậc thiện hữu tri thức
.  Please help me.  Therefore,
đấy. Giúp cho mình đấy. Thế cho nên là
those of you who are of the highest spiritual level should understand that when the mind is focused on
các quý đạo yếu thấy rằng khi tâm chếu
offering gratitude to the master,
hòn quán bạch lễ tri ân sư phụ ấ thì tâm
how should the mind be focused on expressing that gratitude?  All the
chế hòn quán tri ân thế nào? Tất cả các
good deeds of even the youngest child originate from
công đức lành của con nhỏ nhất cũng từ
the master.  That's correct.
nơi sư phụ mà ra. Đấy là chuẩn rồi. Cụm
This phrase is perfect, word for word,
từ này là chuẩn cho đến từng từ một phải
right?  Without my master, I wouldn't have been able to accomplish
không? Nếu không có sư phụ thì mình đâu
any good deeds
có thành tựu được các công đức lành nào
in this lifetime.  It is impossible to
trong cái kiếp này đâu. Không thể tăng
cultivate one's bodhicitta (enlightenment mind).  If
trưởng được tâm bồ đề của mình. Nếu mà
these events hadn't happened, I wouldn't have
không có các cái sự việc này thì mình
felt like I had overcome the obstacles
thấy là mình vượt qua các chướng ngại
.  Life is full of obstacles.
đâu. Cuộc đời này có chướng ngại mà.
In this life, the mind, the heart, and the
Trong cái cuộc đời này tâm chế hòn quán
practice of Buddhism are filled with many
có tu tập Phật pháp thì có rất nhiều chữ
obstacles. Overcoming
ngại và mình đã vượt qua được cái chữ
these obstacles is thanks to virtuous friends and teachers, is
ngại đó là cũng nhờ bậc thiện hữu tri
n't it, dear fellow practitioners? Without them, we would
không các quý đạo hữu không có là mình
n't have been able to overcome them. If we didn't have these
không vượt được qua đó mình không có cái
obstacles,
chướng ngại và mình không vượt qua được
how could we accumulate
chướng ngại thì làm sao mình tích lũy
merit? (Contemplation continues.) The virtuous young boy respectfully bowed and asked, "
được các công đức của mình được đó chứn
Please, Venerable Saint,
bạch rằng cúi Xin Đức Thánh vì tôi mà
teach me how a Bodhisattva should practice Bodhisattva conduct?"
dạy Bồ Tát phải học Bồ Tát hạnh thế nào?
How should one practice the Bodhisattva path?  How should one attain
Phải tu Bồ Tát Hạnh thế nào? Phải đến Bồ
Bodhisattva practice?
Tát Hạnh thế nào?
How did the Buddha truly practice the Bodhisattva path?
Phật thật hành Bồ Tát hạnh thế nào? Phải
How should one practice the Bodhisattva path?  How should one enter the
tịnh Bồ Tát hạnh thế nào? Phải nhập Bồ
Bodhisattva path?  How should one achieve the
Tát hạnh thế nào? Phải thành tựu Bồ Tát
Bodhisattva path?  How should one conform to the Bodhisattva's conduct
hạnh thế nào? Phải tùy thuận Bồ Tát hạnh
?  We must remember how to practice the Bodhisattva path
thế nào? Phải ghi nhớ Bồ Tát hạnh thế
, how to broaden the Bodhisattva path, and
nào, phải thêm rộng Bồ Tát hạnh thế nào,
how to quickly bring about the perfection of the Samantabhadra path
phải làm thế nào cho Phổ Hiền Hạnh mau
.  Do you, fellow practitioners, think that the
được viên mãn. Có quý đạo hữu thấy là
desire of Sudhana to attain supreme enlightenment was
cái tâm mà cần cầu vô thượng bồ đề có
immense?  The desire to seek something is immense.
lớn không? Cái tâm cần cầu rất là lớn.
It is far beyond our reach.
Nó vượt xa xa so với chúng ta. Chúng ta
What do we pray for every day?  They just crave food,
hàng ngày thì chỉ cầu gì? Cầu ăn, cầu
clothing, entertainment, gossip, and go around
mặc, cầu chơi, cầu thị phi, đi chỗ này
talking about things here and there.  There is nothing called
nói chuyện chỗ kia thôi. Chả gì gọi là
mind or intention; it is all very mundane.  So, today we
tâm ý nó rất là phàm. Cho nên hôm nay
are learning this to strive towards becoming a
học cái này để chúng ta hướng tới vị
virtuous and talented person, and
thiện tài đồng tử là để cho nâng cao cái
what is the purpose of this?  Elevate our hearts,
gì? Nâng cao cái tâm của chúng ta lên,
elevate our minds,
nâng cao cái trí của chúng ta lên, nâng
elevate our aspirations.  Is
cao cái ước nguyện của chúng ta lên. Có
that right?  People wish to know something, but all
phải không? Người ta ước biết cái gì,
I know is that I wish I
mình chỉ biết là muốn ước xem là cái
knew what this dish tastes like.  Hurry up and
biết cái món này nó có vị gì. làm mau
go to Thang Nuong to get the money so we can go
mau đến thắng nương để đi lấy tiền để đi
eat that delicious food.  It's a very slight sting.
ăn cái vị đấy thôi. Rất là nhỏ nhói. Ở
What do we need to know here?  I need to know that I humbly
đây là cần biết cái gì? Cần biết là cúi
beg the holy one to teach me
xin đức thánh vì tôi mà dạy Bồ Tát phải
how a Bodhisattva should practice Bodhisattva conduct.  Let me
học Bồ Tát hạnh thế nào? Thôi Tâm Chến
reread it once more to make myself happy.
Quán đọc lại lần nữa cho mình hoan hỉ.
How should one practice the Bodhisattva path?  How should one attain
Phải tu Bồ Tát Hạnh thế nào? Phải đến Bồ
Bodhisattva practice?  How did the Buddha truly practice the Bodhisattva path
Tát Hạnh thế nào? Phật thật hành Bồ Tát
?  So, how exactly did those Buddhas
hạnh thế nào? Tức là các đức Phật đấy
practice the Bodhisattva path?
thật hành Bồ Tát hạnh như thế nào?
How should one practice the Bodhisattva path?  How should one enter the
Phải tịnh Bồ Tát hạnh thế nào? Phải nhập
Bodhisattva path?  How should one achieve the
Bồ Tát hạnh thế nào? Phải thành tựu Bồ
Bodhisattva path?  How should one conform to the Bodhisattva's conduct
Tát hạnh thế nào? Phải tùy thuận Bồ Tát
?  How should we remember the Bodhisattva's conduct
hạnh thế nào? Phải ghi nhớ Bồ Tát hạnh
?  How should we broaden the practice of Bodhisattva conduct
thế nào? Phải thêm rộng Bồ Tát Hạnh thế
?  How can we quickly achieve the fulfillment of the Samantabhadra practice
nào? Phải làm thế nào cho Phổ Hiền Hạnh
?  Did any of you
mau được viên mãn? Hay không có quý đạo
fellow practitioners see this?  That's how people pray, you know
hữu thấy hay không? Đấy, người ta cầu
.  So next time I'll try to
như thế chứ nhá. Cho nên lần sau mình cố
pray.  But in reality, when
gắng mình cầu. Thế nhưng thực chất khi
our minds become more enlightened through spiritual practice,
tâm chúng ta tu hành tu hành cao lên rồi
our aspirations will also become higher
thì cái mong cầu của chúng ta nó sẽ cao
.  This young Bodhisattva, Sudhana, has attained a
như vậy. Ngài Thiện Tài Đồng Tử này ngài
high level of spiritual practice, which is why his heart is filled with
tu hành cao lên cho nên là cái tâm ngài
such aspiration.  My fellow practitioners, you can see that
cầu như vậy. Các quý đạo hữu thấy mà xem
when you first started practicing, you made different requests,
lúc bắt đầu tu các quý đạo hữu cầu khác
but now you have made even
nhưng đến bây giờ các quý đạo hữu đã cầu
more requests.  What do you wish for yourself?  By upholding the
thêm rồi. Cầu cho mình gì? Giữ được cái
precepts, one can cultivate mindfulness.  Are
giới, cầu cho mình chánh niệm. Có phải
we asking for more than we deserve?  Now, the
là chúng ta cầu hơn rồi không? Bây giờ
Buddhist community aspires to cultivate
là khối Phật tử là mong muốn cho mình có
mindfulness.  I didn't get electrocuted
chánh niệm rồi đấy. Không bị phóng giật
.  Each time we experience a sudden impulse, we
rồi đấy. Mỗi lần phóng giật xong chúng
remember it and return to
ta nhớ lại chúng ta lại quay về chánh
mindfulness.  We want to be
niệm. Chúng ta muốn chúng ta chánh niệm
more mindful.  Does
nhiều hơn. Thế có phải là theo cái sự tu
this practice lead to the enhancement of our aspirations
tập này mà mong cầu của chúng ta được
?  Elevated.
tăng thượng không? Tăng thượng. Thế cho
Therefore, when we sincerely aspire to attain
nên khi mình phát tâm chân thật, phát
supreme enlightenment, and
tâm cần cầu vô thượng bồ đề, chúng ta
begin practicing the Bodhisattva path,
bắt đầu thực hành công hạnh bồ đề rồi
our aspiration
thì chúng ta cái cần cầu của chúng ta
increases.
lại tăng lên.
Because the enlightened mind sees that
Bởi vì tâm chiếu hản quán thấy rằng các
those esteemed fellow practitioners are practicing the Bodhisattva path
quý đạo hữu ấy thực hành công hạnh bồ đề
and cultivating the six harmonies—what does that mean?  I
mà thực hành lục hòa đấy là gì? Xin sám
repent for this act of losing mindfulness, so
hối vì việc này mất chánh niệm cho nên
what am I hoping for?  Practicing the six harmonies leads to
là xin mong gì? Thực hành lục hòa được
better results.  That is already a superior Dharma practice
tốt hơn. Cái đấy là đã là pháp tăng
.  Is that right?  The French have become more
thượng rồi đấy. Có phải không? Pháp tăng
powerful.  So, if one wishes to
thượng rồi đấy. Thì mong cầu mình thực
increase their practice of the six harmonies, what does one wish for?   The
hành lục hòa tăng lên thì mong cầu gì?
seeds of enlightenment are growing.  Is it because the six harmonies
Hạt giống bồ đề tăng lên. Tại vì lục hòa
give rise to all Buddhas?
sinh ra chư Phật mà có phải không? Đấy
Eventually, when that merit
thì tới một lúc nào đó cái công đức đấy
accumulates, our minds will open,
nó nhiều lên rồi thì trí chúng ta sẽ mở
and our requests will be essentially the
và chúng ta sẽ cần cầu thế này không
same.  We learn so that
khác nhau đâu. Đó chúng ta học để chúng
we may be happy.  We know that
ta hoan hỉ thôi. Chúng ta biết rằng
we diligently practice, observe precepts, and listen to
chúng ta chăm chỉ tu tập giữ giới nghe
Dharma teachings so that we can understand.  We diligently
pháp để chúng ta hiểu. Chúng ta chăm chỉ
practice the six principles of harmony so that our minds may
tu tập các pháp lục hòa để cho tâm chúng
grow closer to the
ta tăng trưởng lên gần cận lên với cái
Bodhisattva mind, right?  So that we
tâm Bồ Tát phải không? Đấy để chúng ta
can dedicate the merit to it, making it pure and free from
được hồi hướng cho nó thanh tịnh không
obstacles.   That
có chứng ngại nha.
's great.
Rất là hay.
With a grateful heart, I respectfully request that you continue reading the scripture.
Tâm chữ ân quán xin đọc tiếp văn kinh.
Excellent, excellent, Thiện Lam Tử!
Lành thay, lành thay này Thiện Lam Tử,
You have made the vow of supreme enlightenment and sought the
ngươi đã phát tâm vô thượng bồ đề cầu
bodhisattva path.  There you go.  The first text is about
hạnh bồ tát. Đấy nhá. Bài một thì là
cultivating the aspiration for supreme enlightenment, and this second text is about seeking the
phát tâm vô thượng bồ đề, bài hai này là
Bodhisattva path.  O virtuous man, if
cầu hạnh Bồ Tát. Này thiện nam tử, nếu
there are sentient beings who develop the aspiration for supreme enlightenment,
có chúng sanh phát tâm vô thượng bồ đề,
this is a very difficult task.  That's too difficult.  How
đây là việc rất khó. Khó quá chứ. Bao
many lifetimes have I lived? I don't know.  But it's
nhiêu kiếp mình không biết nhỉ? Mà phát
difficult to awaken the true mind.
tực tâm khó chứ.
Many people make a vow this year, but then next year they
Đầy người phát tâm năm nay rồi sang năm
ask to be allowed to stop practicing Buddhism.  I took a break from monastic life
lại xin cho con thôi không tu nữa. Nghỉ
because of busy schedules, because of troubles with fellow
tu vì việc bận, nghỉ tu vì phiền não với
Buddhists, and because I left the monastery due to
Phật tử, nghỉ tu vì ra khỏi đạo tràng vì
something I wasn't satisfied with.  That's considered a
tôi có điều chưa vừa ý. Thế coi như là
difficult achievement in cultivating the Bodhi mind.  It's not
phát được cái tâm bồ đề khó đấy. Không
easy.  Having already developed the Bodhicitta aspiration,
phải dễ đâu ạ. Đã có thể phát bồ đề tâm
yet still striving for Bodhisattva practice, this becomes
rồi lại cầu bồ đề hạnh, việc này lại
infinitely more difficult.  It's very difficult.  Now, if
càng khó gấp bội. Khó lắm. Bây giờ mà
our Buddhist followers only ask for more
Phật tử nhà mình ý chỉ xin thêm cái công
practice of the Bodhisattva path, let's all
hạnh bồ đề thực hành thôi là chúng ta
agree and approve it.  Just submit a
hãy ý hòa đồng duyệt thôi. Phát một cái
request for approval.  It must have been very difficult,
nguyện ý hòa đồng duyệt thôi. Đã khó lắm
right?  It's very difficult.
ấy chứ phải không? Khó lắm.
O virtuous man, if you wish to attain all-encompassing
Này thiện nam tử nếu muốn thành tựu nhất
wisdom, you must resolve to seek true and virtuous
thiết chủng trí thời phải quyết định cầu
teachers.  That means gradually,
chân thiện tri thức. Tức là lần hồi từng
little by little.  If we wish to attain
chút một. Nếu mình muốn thành tựu được
ultimate wisdom, we must associate with
nhất thiết trí thì mình phải thân cận
virtuous teachers and make offerings to them
bậc thiện tri thức, phải cúng dường các
.  Therefore, this
bậc thiện tri thức. Thế cho nên ở đây là
is another affirmation from
là một cái xác quyết nữa của ngài Văn
Venerable Manjushri.  To achieve the greatest success, one
Thủ Sư Lợi. Đó là muốn thành tựu nhất
must resolve to seek
thiết trùng trí thời phải quyết định cầu
true and virtuous knowledge.  This is a
chân thiện tri thức. Cái này nó là cái
mandatory requirement.  If this connection arises, what difference does the
pháp bắt buộc. Duyên này sinh thì duyên
other connection make?  Newborn.  We must have the good fortune
kia mới gì? Mới sinh. phải có duyên cầu
to be close to truly virtuous and wise people
được thân cận với các bậc chân thiện tri
in order to have the opportunity to
thức thì chúng ta mới có thể có duyên mà
attain omniscience.  Therefore,
thành tựu được nhất thiết trí. Đó này
virtuous men should not tire or be lazy in seeking virtuous knowledge
thiện nam tử cầu thiện tri thức chớ có
.  That is, Lord
mỏi lười. Tức là ngài ngài Văn Thù Sư
Manjushri is repeating it again.  Seek knowledge and wisdom,
Lợi nhắc lại lần nữa. Cầu thiện trí thức
but do not tire yourself out, do not be
nhưng mà chớ có mỏi người, không được
lazy, and do not feel tired.  Remember that?  If you're tired, you
lười, không thấy mệt. Nhớ chưa? Mệt thì
have to lift yourself up; if you're lazy, you
phải tự mình xách tấn mình lên, lười thì
have to overcome your laziness.  It's like some
phải tự bỏ cái lười đi. Giống như là có
people practice Buddhism for a while, then they don't
người tu một thời gian ấy thì không
like listening to Dharma teachings anymore, they don't like chanting
thích nghe pháp nữa, không thích tụng
scriptures, they don't like practicing anymore, they just sleep.
kinh, không thích tu nữa, ngủ.
Why are you practicing so much asceticism?  Sleeping
Tu gì mà tu nhiều thế? Ngủ
requires overcoming laziness.  Go,
nó phải qua được cái tâm lười. Đi các
dear friends.  Through laziness.  Regarding the
quý đạo yêu. Qua cái tâm lười. Đối với
true Dharma, we must have a joyful heart and a positive attitude
chánh pháp mình phải được cái tâm hoan
towards the Buddha's teachings; only then can
hỉ cơ với Phật pháp thì lúc bấy giờ
we consider ourselves to have
chúng ta mới tính được là chúng ta có
a good level of self-awareness.  So
cái phần tự giác tốt. Đó cho nên bây giờ
what should we do now?  We must try to use
chúng ta phải gì? phải cố gắng dùng đạo
our fellow practitioners, using the
hữu của mình, dùng các bậc thiện tri
lesser-known and virtuous individuals to push things forward for us.  Is
thức nho nhỏ đẩy cho chúng ta đã. Có
that right?  Do not become complacent when you see a virtuous person;
phải không? Thấy thiện tri thức chớ có
that is, do not consider seeing a
nhàm đủ, tức là chớ có thấy thiện tri
virtuous person as they are and then be content with that.
thức như thế mà đã đủ.
Whatever wise teacher teaches, one should always
Thiện tri thức có dạy bảo điều chi đều
comply.  It's up to you.  As for me, I argue rather stubbornly
tùy thuận. Tùy thuận nhá. Còn mình thì
.  Is that right?  If a
cãi nhám nhám ấy cơ. Có phải không? Nếu
wise person tells you to practice in
thiện tri thức người ta bảo mình tu thế
this way, then you should practice in this way.  After
này nên thực hành thế này. Sau sau khi
hearing that a particular Dharma is a
mình nghe thấy cái pháp đấy là pháp
wholesome Dharma, a Dharma that benefits oneself and all sentient
thiện, pháp có lợi ích cho mình, lợi ích
beings, that helps one attain
cho chúng sinh, giúp cho mình được giác
enlightenment, and that helps one eliminate
ngộ, giúp cho mình được trừ bỏ những cái
unwholesome thoughts, then one must practice it.
bất thiện tâm thì mình phải thực hành.
Is that right?  But there's still a lot to argue about here.
Có phải không? Chứ đây thì còn cãi lắm.
Well, we're just ordinary beings, so why should
Thôi thì mình đang là chúng sinh mà cho
we practice so much spiritual cultivation?  Where the skillful
nên bảo mình tu gì lắm. Nơi thiện xảo
means of wise knowledge are employed, do not find
phương tiện của thiện tri thức chớ thấy
fault.  This particular aspect,
lỗi lầm. Cái chỗ này ấy thì kính thưa
esteemed fellow practitioners, is a rather advanced level of Dharma
quý đạo hữu là cái pháp này nó hơi cao
.
một chút rồi.
Often, we tend to look for faults in the person
Thường ấy chúng ta thường xem cái người
teaching us so that we can
dạy chúng ta có lỗi gì không để chúng ta
scrutinize them.  But once one begins practicing the
soi mói. Thế nhưng mà khi vào thực hành
Bodhisattva path, they obey
Bồ Tát đạo rồi người ta vâng lời một
absolutely.  Let's use the image of the Lord's heart as an
cách tuyệt đối. Ở đây tâm chúa quán lấy
example here.  That's the sutra of Master La Tien
ví dụ nhá. cái bài kinh của ngài La Tiên
that we studied.  When Venerable Na
mà chúng ta đã học đấy. Thì khi ngài Na
Tien was studying under that holy monk, he
Tiên ngài học của vị Thánh Tăng ấy ngài
learned a great deal from the Tripitaka scriptures and
ngài học rất là nhiều Tam Tạng Kinh Điển
memorized them all.  That means,
ngài thuộc hết rồi. Tức là ngài là gọi
initially, he was just called a learned man.  He
lúc đầu ngài chỉ là đa văn thôi. Ngài
memorized it all.  Then, in his contemplation, he
học thuộc hết. Thế xong rồi thì tâm chế
remembered a time when he was debating
quán nhớ là có một lần đi biện biện tài
with another person—that is, engaging in what
với lại một cái người khác tức là cùng
people call a debate—
cùng nhau mà người ta gọi là tranh biện
about this scripture, about what is
ấy về cái việc kinh này này đó về cái về
called scholarship.
gọi là học vấn thì ngài có bị phiền não
He was troubled by something, and then a holy
ngài có bị phiền não cái gì đấy xong rồi
monk taught him.  So
mới vị thánh tăng mới dạy ngài. Thế là
he discarded all of that writing.  When he went
ngài mới bỏ hết cả văn ấy đi. Ngài đi
into the forest to practice meditation, he had to put it
vào rừng ngài tu phải tu thiền định tức
into practice, not just
là phải thực tập chứ không phải chỉ có
study literature.  It's not just
học văn nữa đâu. không phải chỉ không
about studying the Dharma anymore, but about practicing it.  Because
phải pháp học nữa mà pháp hành. Do ở
of that practice,
trong cái pháp hành đấy thì lúc đấy là
he was assigned to carry water
ngài được sai đi gánh nước, gánh nước
up to the temple, which was on the mountaintop, while
lên chùa thì chùa ở trên đỉnh núi còn
he had to carry the water from the
ngài thì phải gánh từ dưới
foot of the mountain all the way up.  Carrying the load until it was
dưới chân núi đi lên. Gánh được đến lúc
very, very tiring, was the
mà phải gánh được rất là cũng rất là mệt
only way to fill the water jug.  So
nên mới đầy được cái chung nước. Thì
we thought that if we went from the bottom of the mountain all the way
chúng ta nghĩ là nếu từ dưới đỉnh núi đi
up, it would take until nightfall to fill the
lên là phải đến tối rồi mới đầy được
cup.  After walking around for a while, we finally arrived at the place where
chung. đi mấy vòng thì nên đến nơi thì
the master, whom we called our teacher,
cái vị thầy ấ gọi là sư phụ đấy mới lấy
kicked over the water jar with his foot.  So
chân đạp đổ cái cái chum nước ấy đi. Thế
he patiently went down to fetch
là ngài nhẫn nhục lại đi xuống gánh
water again.  So what does that mean?   I'm
nước. Thế cho nên ở chỗ đấy là nói gì?
talking about this very spot.  Where the skillful
Là nói chính cái chỗ này này. Nơi thiện
means of wise knowledge are employed, do not
xảo phương tiện của thiện tri thức chớ
find fault.  What is the first part?  Follow the example of a virtuous and knowledgeable person
thấy lỗi lầm. Cái vế trên là cái gì? Tùy
.  That means you have to practice what you're taught
thuận bậc thiện tri thức. Tức là dạy cái
.  The
gì phải làm cái đấy. Thế xong cái thứ
second thing that reminds us is not to look down on
hai nhắc nhở chúng ta là đừng nhìn cái
our own wise teachers.  Don't see
bậc thiện tri thức của mình. Đừng thấy
their mistakes as merely
lỗi lầm của họ mà mình chỉ biết đó là
skillful means they use to
các cái phương tiện thiện xảo để họ độ
guide you; then, when you practice
cho mình thôi thì khi mình thực hành
accordingly, you will benefit.  Of course, skillful
theo mình sẽ được lợi ích. Đương nhiên
means are
là các thiện thiện xảo phương tiện là
good and not evil at all.  I would never encourage
thiện chứ không có gì là ác cả. Không
you to do anything wrong or
xui mình đi làm cái việc bất thiện phạm
illegal.  Do you gentlemen
pháp luật bao giờ đâu. Các quý đợi hiểu
understand this word?  But if we have
rõ chữ này chứ. Nhưng mà chúng ta có một
a habit of constantly observing and
cái thói quen là hay nhìn và hay phán
judging, we absolutely cannot cultivate the
xét thì tuyệt đối không thể nào mà tu
Bodhisattva path.  Why is that?  Because what
hạnh Bồ Tát được. Bởi vì sao? Vì cái mà
people teach us is a
người ta dạy cho mình nó là pháp phương
skillful means that we cannot possibly understand.  For example,
tiện mình không thể biết được. Ví dụ như
Tâm Chư mentioned a
là ở đây Tâm Chư có nói là có một câu
story about an abbot choosing
chuyện mà có vị sư trụ trì đi chọn chọn
his successor.  So, after the
người kế vị cho mình. Đấy, xong vị xu
new abbot, there's this one who's the head of the community, and
trụ trì mới có một ông thủ trúng này,
he's very... as we heard the master
ông ấy rất là, chúng ta được nghe sư phụ
say, this head of the community is the one who
giảng ấy, ông thủ chúng này tức là ông
leads the group, he's a disciple.  Let's just
lãnh thủ chúng là đệ tử đấy. Là mình cứ
call him the manager now.  The
gọi là ông quản chúng bây giờ đấy. Ông
leader of the group is the one who manages them, meaning
thủ chúng là ông quản chúng, tức là ông
he manages them, so he is a
ấy quản nhĩ chúng thì ông ấy là cái
very virtuous person.  They all
người rất là đạo đức. Cả chúng cùng kính
loved each other.  Then the abbot realized that
mến. Thế thì vị sư trụ trì này thấy là
he, too, was about to face impermanence.  Therefore, it is
mình cũng sắp vô thường rồi. Thế thì mới
highly desirable to find a
rất là mong muốn mà nhận chọn được một
disciple to succeed oneself.  However,
cái vị đệ tử để thay mình. Thế nhưng vị
this disciple must first possess considerable
đệ tử này thì phải có thứ nhất là thực
cultivation ability, and second, the entire group
lực tu tập, thứ hai là cả chúng phải
must obey him before he can be
phải tuân tuân thủ thì mới có thể có thể
entrusted with authority and taught;
mà giao quyền được, mới có thể dạy dỗ
otherwise, the brothers will become jealous of
chúng được chứ không thì anh em lại ganh
each other.  So the new abbot falsely accused
tị nhau. Thế là vị sư trụ trì mới lại vu
the head monk of theft
oan cho cái thầy thủ chúng này ăn cắp
and expelled him, but the head monk
rồi đuổi thầy thủ chúng đi thì thầy thủ
once again turned to the abbot and
chúng lại một lòng hướng về thầy mà sám
repented.  If anyone harbors an unwholesome thought towards
hối. một ý niệm nào khởi bất thiện với
the teacher, they should stand somewhere or kneel
thầy rồi hằng ngày đứng ở đâu ở quỳ ở
outside the gate every day to beg for forgiveness.  Then,
ngoài cổng để xin. Thế xong rồi thì bắt
the monk said that
đầu là lúc bấy giờ là vị sư mới nói là
from now on, he had to do all sorts of
từ nay phải đi làm tất cả những cái việc
menial tasks to atone for his sins. The head
giơ ráy để mà sám hối tội nỗi thì coi
monk obeyed the master
như là ông thủ chúng này vâng lời thầy
to the point that even though he didn't steal, if
đến mức độ mình không ăn cắp nhưng mà
the master accused him of stealing, he would still confess to it
thầy bảo mình ăn cắp mình vẫn nhận tội
.  After confessing to the theft, I
ăn cắp. nhận tội ăn cắp rồi thì mình đi
decided to go and fetch water and clean the toilets to
mình quyết nhà gánh nước dọn nhà xí để
atone for my crime of stealing before them.
sám hối cái tội ăn cắp đấy trước chúng.
Do you fellow practitioners find this level of forbearance astonishing?
khiếp không?
Isn't it terrifying to endure humiliation?  Those are the
Nhẫn nhục khiếp không? Đấy là các bậc
teachings of wise and virtuous people.
thiện tri thức dạy cho mình đấy.
Teach this guy who's in charge a lesson.  And then, in
Dạy cho cái ông thủ chúng này. Thế đến
the end, this person had
cuối cùng khi mà vị này coi như là chịu
endured all their contempt.
nhẫn hết cái sự khinh bỉ của chúng. Các
Just imagine how contemptible that is
quý đạo hữu cứ hình dung ra xem khinh
!
không?
I'm a kind of guardian who
Mình là một cái ông thủ chúng mà luôn
always teaches them.  In place of their master, they are now being taught.   My
luôn dạy chúng. Thay sư phụ dạy chúng.
master told me to teach them.  Now my
Sư phụ bảo mình dạy chúng. Đến bây giờ
master says I stole.
sư phụ bảo mình ăn cắp. Trong cái quá
He was very grateful for what he learned during that learning process
trình học được ấy là ông ấy rất là biết
.  Being grateful to one's teacher is essential to
ơn. Biết ơn sư phụ phải biết ơn thì mới
avoid harboring ill intentions.  If
không khởi tâm bất thiện được. Hằng ngày
we are ungrateful every day, negative thoughts will
chúng ta không biết ơn thì tâm bất thiện
arise immediately.  Is that right?  Just
nó sinh ra ngay. Có phải không? Giống
like a child who is ungrateful to their parents is
như một đứa con lại không biết ơn cha mẹ
naturally very unkind
thì đương nhiên là nó rất là bất thiện
to them.  Is that right?  But a
với cha mẹ. Có phải không? Nhưng cái đứa
grateful person is never wicked.  Regardless of
biết ơn thì không bao giờ bất thiện. Dù
the parents' character, it will not be evil.
cha mẹ thế nào nó cũng không bất thiện.
Therefore, it is said that by constantly remembering gratitude,
Cho nên người ta gọi là hằng niệm tâm ơn
this person becomes a
thì người này trở lên trở thành thánh
saint who constantly remembers gratitude.
thiện được thường niệm tâm ơn.
So, this chief official... I'm really
Thế thì ông thủ chúng này thực sự là
putting myself in his shoes,
mình đặt cái địa vị mình vào ông ấy đi
aren't I?  I wholeheartedly devoted myself to
có phải không? mình hết lòng dốc lực
doing everything the teacher taught me, and I
thầy dạy gì mình mình làm đấy mình lại
even had to take on the responsibility of
còn phải nhận cái trách nhiệm là thay
teaching them in their place.  My teacher taught me that way, and
thầy dạy chúng nữa. Thầy dạy mình như
I did everything for
thế rồi tất cả các việc mình làm hết cho
them until now, and now he's accusing me of stealing.
chúng đến bây giờ thầy bảo mình ăn cắp.
Those who lack gratitude will boast about their
Nếu mà người không có tâm ơn thì sẽ kể
contributions.  I did that, and this guy reacted in
công. Tôi đã làm như thế mà cái ông này
this way or that way, maybe even cursing or beating him
thế này thế kia có khi chửi đánh cho ông
up, right?  Then, spreading rumors and gossiping about
trận đúng không? Rồi đi nói xấu rồi đuôi
others is considered betraying your teacher and harming your friends, is
đủ các thứ là phản thầy hại bạn ngay có
n't it?  But
phải không? Thế nhưng mà cái vị thủ
this ringleader admitted to stealing
chúng này là tự nhận mình đã ăn cắp như
through specific actions, did
thế bằng các hành động cụ thể có phải
n't he?  By performing specific acts of
không? bằng các hành động cụ thể là sám
repentance outside the main gate, they wouldn't let anyone in
hối ở ngoài cổng tam quan có cho vào
.  Later, this old monk said that since he was
đâu. Về sau là cụ sư này cụ bảo là sám
repenting in that way, he would let him come here to
hối như thế thì cụ cho vào đây để mà đi
atone for his sins by cleaning toilets
sám hối cái lỗi đó là đi dọn nhà vệ
, sweeping from morning till night, carrying
sinh, đi quét tước từ sáng đến đêm, gánh
water, and doing other arduous tasks.
nước, làm các công việc lặng nhọc. Vị
This leader does everything, and once he's done it all, you
thủ chúng này làm hết, làm hết thì đấy
esteemed monks can imagine what it's like.
các quý đạo ý cứ hình dung ra đi. Lúc
Before, when I was above them, I
trước thì mình đứng trên chúng thì mình
had to tell them this and that.  Now that
phải nói chúng thế này thế kia. Bây giờ
they see this, what will people do?
thấy như thế thì người ta sẽ gì? Còn
Many of them haven't yet attained enlightenment.  If they can cultivate virtue,
nhiều chúng chưa tu được chứ. Có chúng
people will understand that,
tu được thì người ta sẽ thông cảm là
well, he made a mistake, or it was just for a
thôi thì người thì còn có lỗi hay là một
moment, but otherwise he's always been good.
phút đấy thôi chứ mọi khi ông tốt. Người
People think that way because they believe he must have committed a
ta nghĩ thế vì người ta nghĩ là ông có
crime for him to confess.  Okay,
lỗi tội thì ông mới nhận tội mà. Thôi
you'll have to wait, right?  That
quý đợi thế đúng không? Thế thì lúc đấy
was really embarrassing then.  Back then, we ended up eating
là xì vả lắm rồi. Lúc đấy lại ăn cơm
their leftovers.  They
thừa của chúng đấy chứ. Chúng ăn thừa
only get to eat the leftovers.  Do you see that, my esteemed friends
mới được ăn cơm chứ. Đấy các quý đạo hữu
?  Imagine leaving.  If we can
thấy không? hình dung ra đi. Chúng ta
imagine it, we can see
hình dung ra thì chúng ta thấy được cái
what kind of virtue this leader possessed.  In the end, having perfected all his
nào. Đến cuối cùng mà viên mãn các công
virtues, he endured and acted in such a way that his
đức rồi, ngài nhẫn nhục như thế, làm như
master realized he could never again
thế rồi sư sư phụ ấ thấy là không lúc
see his disciple be
nào mà thấy cái vị đệ tử của mình có thể
wicked.  That means all the
bất thiện được nữa. Tức là làm hết các
hard work has been done.  Everyone has become indifferent to it
cái khổ lao rồi. Mọi người coi thường
, considering it normal, and
hết rồi, cho nó là việc bình thường rồi,
nobody bothers to complain anymore.  No one
không ai thèm chửi nữa rồi. Không ai
curses anymore, no one looks down on them
thèm rủa nữa rồi, không ai thèm coi
anymore.  Because you
thường nữa rồi. Tại vì coi thường sẵn
already looked down on them, right?  No one would dare to look down on them
rồi, có phải không? không ai thèm coi
anymore.  That means all
thường thêm nữa rồi. Tức là tất cả các
forms of forbearance have been exhausted;
pháp nhẫn nhục đã nhẫn nhục hết rồi,
nothing more can be created to require
không còn ai sinh ra cái gì để cho nhẫn
further forbearance.  Then the
nhục thêm được nữa. Thì lúc bấy giờ vị
head monk called everyone in and said, "
sư trưởng mới gọi vào mới nói với mọi
I'm entrusting the temple and the
người là tôi giao chùa giao chúng cho
community to this head monk because he
cái ông thầy thủ chúng này vì ông thầy
didn't steal, but I'm falsely accusing him
thủ chúng không ăn cắp mà tôi trí vu cho
."  So, my esteemed fellow practitioners, do you see that the Venerable Master, the
vậy. Đấy các quý đạo hữu thấy là cái chỗ
head of the community, is able to
này là ngài cái cái vị thủ chúng có thực
practice this?  The practice was
hành được chỗ này không? thực hành được
perfected.  Where skillful means and
viên mãn. Nơi thiện xảo, phương tiện của
wise conduct prevail, do not be deceived.
thiện trí thức chớ thấy nỗi lầm.
That's the place where the teacher teaches us not to
Cái chỗ mà nơi thầy dạy mình đừng có
see people's mistakes.
thấy người ta có lỗi.
If we see others making mistakes,
Nếu thấy người ta có lỗi thì mình làm
how can we practice what we've learned?  If the head monk
sao thực hành được. Nếu ông thủ chúng
thinks this old monk is at fault, is that right
kia thấy ông sư cụ này có lỗi có phải
?  How can
không? Là vu khống cho mình thì làm sao
I learn if they're slandering me?
mà mình học được đây? Thì các cái đức
How can I attain the happiness of patience when I possess those other virtues of forbearance
tính tội nhẫn nhục kia của mình mình làm
?  Is that right
sao được hạnh nhẫn nhục đây? Có phải
?  So, is the Bodhisattva practice
không? Cho nên cái hạnh Bồ Tát là hạnh
patience and forbearance?  So, in
nhẫn nhục có phải không? Thì nơi thiện
this place of virtuous friends and knowledge, have we learned the
hữu tri thức này có phải là học được
virtue of patience?  Therefore, this is a
hạnh nhẫn nhục chưa? Đấy cho nên là bài
wonderful sutra, isn't it, dear fellow practitioners?  Very
kinh hay quá phải không quý đạo hữu? Rất
good and very practical.  Therefore, we
hay và rất thực tế. Cho nên là chúng ta
must understand that when we are students, we
phải biết khi chúng ta là trò chúng ta
must have the virtue of being respectful and esteemed,
phải có cái đức làm trò th quý đợi hữu
not showing
chứ không phải khi chúng ta làm trò
disrespect to our teachers, because that will lead to
chúng ta coi thường người dạy mình là
our downfall.  We see ourselves as
chúng ta bị đổ vỡ đấy. Chúng ta coi mình
equal to the person who taught us.  If
ngang bằng với cái người dạy mình. Chúng
we behave in such an arrogant manner,
ta có cái hành xử ngang như thế là chúng
what will become of us?  It will fall apart.  So what is being taught here
ta sẽ gì? sẽ đổ vỡ. Cho nên ở đây dạy là
?  What teachings did wise teachers impart?
gì? Thiện tri thức có dạy bảo điều gì?
What teachings did the wise teacher impart?  They must all
Thiện tri thức có dạy bảo điều chi? Phải
comply.  As you wish.  "To adapt" means to go along with the
đều tùy thuận. Tùy thuận. Tùy tức là tùy
situation.  That means
vào sự việc mà phải thuận theo. Việc đấy
everything must be done in accordance with the teachings.
là việc gì cũng phải thuận theo lời dạy.
Where the skillful means of wise knowledge are employed,
Nơi thiện xảo phương tiện của thiện tri
do not find fault.  Do you gentlemen find this interesting
thức chớ thấy lỗi lầm. Các quý đợi hữu
?  I have to learn this;
thấy hay không? Cái này mình phải học
I need to learn a lot.
mình học rất nhiều.
There.  Then, at this point,
Đó. Xong rồi lúc này rồi bắt đầu là
Manjushri began to
ngài Văn Thù Sư Lợi mới bắt đầu giới
introduce the first group of virtuous individuals
thiệu đến các bậc thiện tri thức đầu
to come and study.  Here it is.  That is to say, after giving instructions on how to
tiên để đi học. Đây này. Tức là dặn dò
cultivate virtue, one should then be advised
như thế cần cầu tu rồi xong rồi thì dặn
on how to treat virtuous and knowledgeable people
là đối với bậc thiện tri thức phải thế
.  First, offerings must be made.  Secondly, one
nào. Thứ nhất là phải cúng dường. Thứ
must obey and follow the teachings of virtuous teachers, adapting their methods accordingly
hai là phải vâng thuận bậc thiện tri
.
thức tùy thuận mà thực hành theo. Thế
Then we fail to see the mistakes of a truly
rồi thì không được thấy lỗi lầm của bậc
wise person.
thiện tri thức.
After giving the instructions and receiving his
Dặn xong rồi ngài
agreement, the young man named Sudhana began to
Thiện Tài Đồng Tử đồng ý rồi thì bắt đầu
introduce himself.  As for
ngài mới giới thiệu cho đây này. Còn
me, I just introduced things haphazardly, without even
mình thì giới thiệu lung tung quả chưa
reminding people of any ethics, I just
cần dặn người ta đạo đức gì mình đã giới
introduced them, saying things like, "Where are the esteemed people? We have to learn, we have to do this, we
thiệu đi rồi các quý đâu mình học phải
have to do
học đấy đến đây thì phải làm này làm thế
this."
này nhá.
Please continue reading.  In the South,
Đây chế cán xin đọc tiếp. Phương Nam này
there is a country called Thang Lac.  In the country of
có một nước tên là Thắng Lạc. Trong nước
Thang Lac, there is a mountain called Dieu Phong.
Thắng Lạc có tòa núi tên là Diệu Phong.
On that mountain lived a monk named Duc
Trên núi đó có một tỳ kheo tên là Đức
Van.  You should go and ask the monk Duc Van,
Vân. Ngươi nên đến hỏi tỳ kheo Đức Vân,
how should a Bodhisattva practice Bodhisattva conduct?
Bồ Tát phải học Bồ Tát hạnh thế nào?
How should one cultivate the Bodhisattva path, and what kind of patience is required,
Phải tu Bồ Tát hạnh thế nào, nhẫn đến
in order to quickly attain the
phải như thế nào để được mau viên mãn
perfect fulfillment of the Samantabhadra path?  The monk Duc Van will
hạnh phổ hiền? Tỳ kheo Đức Vân sẽ chỉ
instruct you.
bảo cho ngươi.
Do you find this interesting, fellow practitioners?  Do you think the
Các quý đạo hữu thấy hay không? Thấy
teachings of Manjushri are good or
ngài Văn Thù Sư Lợi dạy người có hay
not?  Observe whether this person is capable of teaching
không? Quán sát xem người này có dạy
, and what kind of blessings they possess.
được không, xem phước báo của họ là gì.
After that, encourage them to develop the Bodhi mind
Xong rồi thì khuyến phát cho phát tâm bồ
.  Encouragement to cultivate the Bodhi mind.
đề. Khuyến phát cho phát tâm bồ đề.
People joyfully developed the Bodhi mind, and seeing that
Người ta hoan hỉ phát tâm bồ đề rồi thấy
others needed to learn the Bodhisattva path, they
người ta cần cầu học đạo Bồ Tát thì mới
taught Sudhana that to learn the
dạy cho Thiện Tài Đồng Tử là muốn học
Bodhisattva path, one must first associate with
đạo Bồ Tát thì đầu tiên là phải thân cận
virtuous teachers.   And then, after
bậc thiện tri thức.
meeting a wise and virtuous person,
Rồi gặp bậc thiện tri thức rồi thì phải
what should one do?  One must practice the ritual of offering
gì? Phải thực hành cái pháp cúng dường
to fulfill all wishes.  To achieve
để cầu nhất thiết chí. Mà muốn cầu được
this ultimate goal, one must
nhất thiết chí này thì phải
associate with virtuous and knowledgeable people.  When a wise and
thân cận bậc thiện tri thức. Bậc thiện
knowledgeable person teaches something, one must obey and follow their instructions
tri thức mà dạy bảo cái gì thì phải vâng
.  Yes, follow, comply, and do as
thuận. Vâng thuận theo, tùy thuận làm
instructed, and do not look at the mistakes of
theo và không được nhìn nỗi lầm của bậc
wise people.  Among the
thiện tri thức. Trong các pháp phương
skillful means, that is, the Bodhisattvas
tiện thiện xảo, tức là các đức Bồ Tát
teach us to use skillful means
dạy mình phải dùng các pháp phương tiện
.
thiện xảo.
Like a means of falsely accusing someone of theft,
Giống như là phương tiện vu cho ăn cắp,
it's a clever way to help this man
đấy là thiện xảo để giúp cho ông này
practice patience.  That is called
thực hành được nhẫn nhục. Đấy gọi là
skillful expedient means.  For example,
pháp phương tiện thiện xảo. Ví dụ như
knocking over the water jar of Lord La Tien
đạp đổ cái chum nước của ngài La Tiên,
is a skillful means.
đấy là phương tiện thiện xảo. Có quý đợi
Do you understand what I mean?  A person who is well-versed in literature
hiểu thấy không? Một người đa văn thì
is naturally lazy when it comes to physical matters.  So,
tất nhiên là lười ở thân rồi. Cho nên
what kind of training is it to make them carry water like that?  Train your body.  Therefore,
cái gì? Luyện cái thân. Cho nên là cần
whatever one needs to achieve,
cái gì để thành tựu cho mình thì các bậc
wise and virtuous people will provide
thiện tri thức người ta sẽ có những cái
skillful means to help them put it into
phương tiện thiện xạo để giúp cho mình
practice.  There.  Therefore, in places where
thực hành được. Đấy. Thế cho nên là nơi
virtuous and knowledgeable people reside, one
các bậc thiện thiện tri thức thì không
should not see any fault in their skillful use of
được nhìn thấy họ có lỗi lầm trong cái
expedient methods.  To be honest,
pháp phương tiện thiện xảo. Thực sự ra
when you become a monk, you have to be able to endure being
thì khi đi tu ấy thì phải nhẫn được cái
scolded.
sự mắng mỏ.
Scolding it will suppress its ego.  Those who are weak in spiritual practice
Mắng mỏ nó dẹp trừ bản ngã. Các quý đạo
cannot cultivate themselves if they immediately become angry if anyone provokes them
cái chúng ta nổi sân ngay thì không thể
.  Therefore, the first thing a person who becomes a monk
tu được. Cho nên người đi tu đầu tiên là
must learn is to be patient and endure being scolded.  We see
phải học chữ nhẫn bị mắng. Chúng ta thấy
that the teacher scolded the leader, did
là cái ông thầy ông có mắng mắng vị thủ
n't he?
chúng không?
Besides scolding, of course you have to
Không những mắng thì có đương nhiên là
give something to the thief, then to the terrible person
phải cho đồ ăn cắp rồi thì phải đồ tồi
, the ungrateful person, and all sorts of other bad people.  That's not the case, is it
tệ, đồ vô ơn các thứ các loại chứ. Mỗi
?  He both scolded and
thế đâu phải không? Ông vừa mắng ông còn
beat her.  He didn't just
vừa đánh cho nữa chứ. có phải ông vừa
kick me out, did he? He didn't just stay silent either.
đuổi nữa đâu có phải là không nói đâu.
Therefore, the process of teaching
Thế cho nên là cái quá trình dạy chúng
them is one where we need
ấy là một cái quá trình chúng ta phải có
many means to see if the other
nhiều phương tiện để xem cái người kia
person is willing or not.  To be honest, when
người ta có thuận tâm hay không. Chứ
I'm teaching someone,
thực ra mà nói là mình dạy cái người này
I have to be selective about the
nhưng mình còn phải lừa lựa phải dùng
words I use, so how can that person possibly learn
cái từ này cái người đấy làm sao mà học
?  It must progress from lower to higher levels of Dharma.
được. Nó phải từ pháp thấp đến pháp cao.
One must be patient and tolerant in order to teach
Người ta phải nhẫn nhục được thì mới dạy
effectively.  Is that correct?
được. Có đúng không nào? Cái người mà
Now, fellow practitioners, just try talking to
bây giờ các đạo hữu cứ thử xem đối với
this person
người này mình nói chuyện một cách thoải
comfortably; it's already easy enough.  If we still have to
mái đã là dễ rồi nhá. Nếu mà còn phải
choose, then it's considered difficult.  Then, we have to order
lựa lựa mới nói là khó. Thế rồi sai bảo
each other around to do things, even good deeds
nhau đi làm ấy, các cái việc thiện lại
require orders, right?  Difficult.
còn phải lịnh nhau nữa phải không? Khó.
But to what level do we need to reach?
Nhưng mà chúng ta phải đến cái tầm gì?
Go there and ask for it.  Go there and ask for a job
Đến đấy mà thỉnh. Đến đấy mà thỉnh việc
for me.  So, did that mean I got scolded?   Yes
cho ta làm. Ấ thì có phải ăn mắng không?
.  You have to be patient.  So, based on what
Có chứ. Phải nhẫn nhục chứ. Thế cho nên
we learn from these scriptures,
chúng ta từ những cái bài kinh này chúng
what should we do?   What should we
ta học chúng ta cần làm những cái gì?
cultivate? What do we need to cultivate?
Chúng ta cần tu cái gì, cần phải tu cái
Therefore, if one
gì. Cho nên là tu hành Bồ Tát đạo lại
cannot endure false accusations while practicing the Bodhisattva path, they cannot succeed in their practice
không chịu được vu oan thì không thể tu
.  Is that right?  You can't practice spiritual cultivation if you can't endure being scolded
được. Có phải không? Không chịu ăn mắng
.  Dear fellow practitioners, I, the
thì không tu được. Kính thưa quý đạo hữu
Mind-Contemplating Enlightenment Master, would like to emphasize the
thì tâm chứ quán a xin nhấn mạnh những
fundamental points in this sutra.
cái điều cơ bản trong cái bài kinh này.
Okay, let's continue.
Thế rồi chúng ta tiếp tục nhá.
At that time, the good fortune, the
Lúc đó thiện tài,
good fortune, was the good fortune boy.
thiện tài tức là thiện tài đồng tử đấy.
At that time, the virtuous man conceived the idea that
Lúc đó thiện tài liền phát ý nghĩ rằng
by associating with virtuous and knowledgeable people, he could
do thân cận thiện tri thức mà có thể
diligently and courageously cultivate the ultimate path.
dũng mãnh siêng tu nhất thiết chí đạo.
By associating closely with virtuous and knowledgeable people, one can quickly
Do thân cận thiện tri thức mà có thể mau
develop great aspirations.  Through close association with virtuous and
xuất sanh những đại nguyện. Do thân cận
knowledgeable people, one can endure boundless suffering for the sake of all sentient beings,
thiện tri thức mà có thể vì chúng sinh
even for future eons.  Through
thọ vô biên khổ tận kiếp vị lai. Do thân
associating with virtuous teachers, one can don the armor of great diligence, preaching the Dharma with the
cận thiện tri thức mà có thể mặc áo giáp
sound reverberating throughout the Dharma realm in a single particle; through
pháp tiếng vang khắp pháp giới do thân
associating with virtuous teachers, one can quickly reach
cận thiện tri thức mà có thể mau đến tất
all directions.  Because of close association with virtuous and knowledgeable people, one can cultivate the
cả phương. Do thân cận thiện tri thức mà
Bodhisattva path for all eternity, even within a single strand of hair
ở trong một sợi lông tu Bồ Tát hạnh tận
.  Because of close association with virtuous teachers,
vị lai kiếp. Do thân cận thiện tri thức
in every moment of practicing the Bodhisattva path, even in ignorance of the teachings, one
mà trong mỗi niệm thật hành Bồ Tát hạnh
abides in the state of omniscience.  Through close
dốt giáo an trụ bực nhất thiết trí. Do
association with virtuous and knowledgeable people, one can enter the
thân cận thiện tri thức mà có thể nhập
majestic, powerful, and free paths
những đạo trang nghiêm thần lực tự tại
of all Buddhas.  By associating closely with virtuous and
của tất cả Như Lai. Do thân cận thiện
knowledgeable people, one can frequently access all
tri thức mà có thể thường vào khắp các
realms of Dharma teachings.  Because of close association with virtuous and
môn pháp giới. Do thân cận thiện tri
knowledgeable people, one's connection to the Dharma realm never
thức nên thường duyên pháp giới chưa
arises, yet one can travel throughout the ten directions of the universe
từng động xuất mà có thể qua khắp quốc
.   Do
độ mườ phương.
we see the Good Fortune Boy or
Chúng ta thấy Thiện Tài Đồng Tử hay
not?
không?
In fact, even as listeners of the scriptures,
Thực ra là chúng ta là người nghe kinh
we can see that, for example, if
thôi thì chúng ta cũng thấy là ví dụ như
we think that practicing the Bodhisattva path
là mình nghĩ là thực hành Bồ Tát đạo là
requires generosity, precepts, patience, diligence, and
phải bố thí chỉ giới, nhẫn nhục tinh tấn
meditation, then we also say that
thiền định thì chúng ta cũng bảo là
we must associate with virtuous teachers in order to
chúng ta phải thân cận bậc thiện tri
learn the
thức thì chúng ta mới có thể học được
Dharma of generosity, to help us cultivate a
pháp bố thí, có thể trợ giúp cho mình
generous mind, and to achieve the perfection of generosity
cái tâm bố thí được, thành tựu được bố
.  Is that right
thí ba la mật cho mình được. Có phải
?  Therefore, that's why the Good
không? Đấy, từ đấy cho nên là Thiện Tại
Boy thinks this way, and with such
Đồng Tử tư duy như vậy,
thinking, he naturally holds great
tư duy như vậy thì đương nhiên là sẽ rất
respect for virtuous teachers and
là kính quý bậc thiện tri thức, rất là
cherishes the opportunity to be close to them.
quý cái duyên được gần thiện tri thức.
Because we cherish the opportunity to be close to virtuous and
Vì quý cái duyên được gần bậc thiện tri
knowledgeable people, we obey and follow whatever those virtuous and knowledgeable people teach us
thức cho nên bậc thiện tri thức dạy gì
.
thì cũng vâng thuận theo.
Is that correct, fellow practitioners?  Therefore, it is
Có đúng không có quý đạo hữu? Thế rồi
impossible to tire of
cũng không thể nào mà lại nhàm mỏi cái
seeking close contact with virtuous teachers,
tâm mà cầu cần thân cận thiện tri thức
and one cannot dare to harbor
và cũng không thể nào mà dám khởi tâm
doubt or ill will towards the
nghi, khởi tâm bất thiện đối với pháp
skillful means taught by virtuous teachers
phương tiện của bậc thiện tri thức khi
.  Is that right?  Because they have the
dạy cho mình. Có phải không? Do có cái
right mindset.   The young
tư duy đúng thế này.
boy, filled with joy and happiness, bowed in reverence to
Thiện tài đồng tử hớn hở vui mừng đảnh
Manjushri Bodhisattva.  After
lễ Văn Thù Sư Lợi Bồ Tát. hữu nhiễu vô
countless rounds of admiring glances, they wept in gratitude and departed, heading
số vòng, ân cần chiêm ngưỡng, rơi lệ tạ
south.  That is, only then did the
mà đi qua hướng nam. Tức là sau đó thì
boy Sudhana begin to circumambulate
Thiện Tài Đồng Tử mới bắt đầu đi nhiễu
around the Buddha Manjushri.
quanh ngài Văn Thù Sư Lợi.
Tears of gratitude fall, tears of thankfulness fall,
Rơi lệ cám ơn ấy tri ân ấ rơi lệ rất là
tears of profound appreciation, with heartfelt reverence,
biết ân, ân cần chiêm ngưỡng, chiêm
reverence for the Venerable Manjushri.  After that, he tearfully bid farewell
ngưỡng ngài Văn Thù Sư Lợi. Xong sau đó
and headed south.  Go
thì rơi lệ từ tạ mà đi qua hướng nam. đi
towards the blue direction to reach the place where the
qua hướng lam để đến cái chỗ mà tỳ kheo
monk Duc Van, whom Manjushri just
Đức Vân mà ngài Văn Thù Sư Lợi vừa mới
mentioned, resides.  With tears in his eyes, he bid farewell and headed
nói đấy. Rơi lệ từ tạ mà đi qua hướng
south to the country of Thang Lac, ascending Mount Dieu
Nam đến nước Thắng Lạc lên núi Diệu
Phong, his heart yearning to meet the monk
Phong lòng khao khát muốn được gặp Tỳ
Duc Van so that he could inquire about the conduct of the
kheo Đức Vân để có thể hỏi hạnh của Bồ
Bodhisattva.  And our sermon ends
Tát. Và bài kinh chúng ta dừng lại ở
here.  After listening, do you feel
đây. Các quý đạo hữu nghe xong có thấy
that
là là
we can broaden our
chúng ta có thể mở mang thêm được kiến
knowledge?  And can we dispel our
thức không? Và chúng ta có thể dẹp trừ
afflictions when we listen to
phiền não khi chúng ta nghe cái bài kinh
this sutra?  It helps to eliminate some
này không? Dẹp trừ được một số phiền
worries.  It's frustrating when we're
não. Phiền não khi chúng ta được người
taught something but still feel completely clueless.  Is that right
ta dạy mình lại còn trống trái. Có phải
?  They refused to listen, then met a
không? không chịu nghe theo thế rồi gặp
wise person, and now they want to leave.
thiện tri thức rồi muốn bỏ đi.
Now, I must consider all
Mình bây giờ mình phải coi tất cả những
those who guide me in my practice as
người nào xách tấn cho mình tu tập là
my spiritual friends.  In our spiritual community,
thiện tri thức của mình. Trong đạo tràng
whoever supports us
chúng ta ai xách tấn cho chúng ta thì
is a good friend to one another.
chúng ta là thiện tri thức của nhau.
We have to view things from childhood to adulthood in this way,
Chúng ta phải coi từ nhỏ đến lớn như thế
not just encountering a
chứ không phải là mình cứ gặp được Bồ
Bodhisattva every time.  Is that right?  Then we must
Tát đâu. Có phải không? Thì mình phải
consider those lesser-known, virtuous individuals.
coi những cái bậc thiện trí thức nhỏ. Ví
For example, today, I'm not a
dụ như là hôm nay là mình người không đi
monk, and someone reminds me, "Why don't you become a monk
tu lại có người nhắc mình là thôi hôm
today and start a family?"  That's also a
nay đi tu bát con trai đi. Đấy cũng là
wise teacher who helped me acquire the good
bậc thiện tri thức giúp cho mình cái tốt
qualities I already possessed, isn't it?  Then I saw that
lành đã có phải không? Thế thì thấy này
my fellow practitioner said, "Let's stop practicing asceticism and have a
thấy đạo hữu mình nói là thôi tu bắt con
son instead."  Why are you rushing so much?  Just
trai đi. Giục gì mà giục lắm thế? Thôi
touch the screen,
chạm máy luôn
no more comments.  That's not
không không ý kiến nữa. Thế là không
allowed, is it?  So, when we listen to
được phải không? Thế chúng mình nghe cái
this sutra, we should observe
bài kinh này thì mình sẽ sẽ quán sát xem
our surroundings to see who
xung quanh mình là mình ai là những bậc
our wise mentors are, who
thiện trí thức của mình, ai là những
encourages us to practice, and we should
người sách tấn mình tu tập thì mình phải
try to get close to them instead of blocking their access.
cố mà thân cận chứ đừng chặn máy nhá.
Don't think that just because the phone isn't answering, it's a good idea.
Đừng có mà thấy máy không nghe nhá.
Thanks to them, I've been able to progress,
Nhờ họ mà mình được tinh tấn lên đấy
right?  So, we'd call that
phải không? Thì đấy mình gọi là thiện
just a small act of kindness, right?  But
tri thức nhỏ thôi đã phải không? Mà bên
alongside great and wise people, there must also be
cạnh thiện tri thức lớn phải có thiện
lesser and wise people.  So, besides
tri thức nhỏ. Đấy, bên cạnh ngài Văn Thù
Manjushri, who else do we have to meet next?   Venerable Monk Duc
Sư Lợi lại phải đến gặp ngài gì đây?
Van.  Here it is.  Is that right
Ngài Tỳ Kheo Đức Vân. Đây này. Có phải
?  That's the real Venerable Monk Duc Van.  And
không? Đấy mới là Tỳ Kheo Đức Vân. Còn
up there is the Bodhisattva Manjushri.  Because
trên kia là ngài Văn Thù Sư Lợi cơ. Vì
the Venerable Monk Duc Van is practicing
ngài Tỳ Kheo Đức Vân là đang tu cái pháp
this Dharma, what kind of practice is it in accordance with
này tương ưng với lại cái sự tu tập của
?  This is the place of the Good Fortune Boy now.
gì? Của Thiện Tài Đồng Tử bây giờ. Xong
After finishing his studies with Bhikkhu Duc Van,
đến lúc học xong ở chỗ Tỳ kheo Đức Vân
Bhikkhu Duc Van will know
rồi thì Tỳ Kheo Đức Vân sẽ biết được là
who else he needs to practice with.  So,
cần phải tu tập ở chỗ ai nữa. Cho nên tỳ
will the monk Duc Van refer us elsewhere
kheo Đức Vân sẽ giới thiệu đi chỗ khác
?  Okay, there you go.  So, since
phải không? Đó nhá. Thế cho nên là chúng
we are currently practicing at the stage of sowing seeds of opportunity, we should
ta đang tu tập ở thành phần gieo duyên
strive to participate, strive to
rồi thì cố gắng lên để dự tủy cố gắng
listen, strive to become official,
lên dự thính rồi cố gắng lên chính thức
and strive to do what?  The committee of the
rồi cố gắng lên làm gì? là ban sử đạo
ancient temple's history department is determined to strive diligently.   That
tràng cổ khánh phát tâm tinh tấn nhá.
means it happens gradually.  If we keep learning from
Tức là nó từ từ như thế đấy. Phải học
one place to another,
hết chỗ này đến chỗ kia thì lúc nào
we'll always find a kind and knowledgeable friend or mentor,
chúng ta cũng có bậc thiện hữu tri thức
right?  To help
tương ưng thôi phải không? Để giúp cho
us achieve good things.  Now
chúng ta những điều tốt lành. Đó sau đây
we will move on to the second part, which is the
chúng ta sẽ bước sang phần thứ hai là đề
topic of the restaurant.
mục quán.
First heading.
Hạt đề mục thứ nhất.
Because of the aspiration for the Bodhi mind and the wisdom of the Buddha, one
Vì mong cầu tâm bồ đề trí tuệ Phật mà
develops the aspiration to seek close contact with virtuous
phát tâm cần cầu
teachers.
thân cận bậc thiện tri thức.
Here, it's said that the essential
Ở đây thì nói là nhất thiết trí thì tâm
wisdom is the mind's contemplation; let's use the term "
chú quán a xin đưa luôn từ là trí tuệ
Buddha's wisdom" for easier understanding and relatable reference.
Phật cho dễ hiểu và gần gũi.
The second topic is to reflect on the virtuous teachers who
Đề mục thứ hai, tư duy về các bậc thiện
are currently helping me
tri thức hiện tại đang giúp mình tu tập
cultivate the Bodhi mind
phát tâm bồ đề
at the monastery,
ở tại tổ,
at the Dharma center, or
tại đạo tràng,
at the club
tại câu lạc bộ
—the monks.   He
là chư tăng.
is my master.  So let's consider
là sư phụ. Thế chúng ta tư duy xem là
how close we are to this wise and virtuous person in the present moment.
thức này thế nào? Từ nơi các bậc thiện
What benefits can we gain from these wise and virtuous people
tri thức này chúng ta được cái lợi gì
?  It means we have developed a sincere desire to be close to each other
phải không? Là chúng ta phát tâm thân
.
cận nha.
We call it being fortunate to be close to virtuous and knowledgeable people for all eternity
Chúng ta gọi là đời đời kiếp kiếp được
.  There.
thân cận bậc thiện tri thức. Đấy.
Third topic.  The thought of
Đề mục thứ ba. Tư duy về các hạnh cần
seeking virtuous and wise guidance never tires the mind.
cầu bậc thiện tri thức không nhàm mỏi.
This is where the need to tirelessly seek out virtuous and knowledgeable people arises
Chỗ này là hạnh cần cầu bậc thiện tri
.  Through the benefits of being
thức không nhàm mỏi. Qua việc lợi ích
close to virtuous and knowledgeable people.   The
khi gần thiện tri thức.
disadvantage of not having a wise and
Qua việc bất lợi khi không có bậc thiện
knowledgeable person around.  That means we must think about
tri thức. Tức là chúng ta phải tư duy để
how to cultivate the
làm sao chúng ta khởi được cái tâm mà
desire to be close to virtuous and knowledgeable people without
muốn thân cận bậc thiện tri thức không
getting tired of it. By being close to
nhàm mỏi qua cái việc là chúng ta gần
virtuous and knowledgeable people, we can achieve
bậc thiện tri thức thì chúng ta được thế
this.
này. Chúng ta không gần các bậc thiện
We are at this disadvantage because we are not close to wise and virtuous people
tri thức thì chúng ta bị bất lợi thế
.  Therefore, it is from
này. Cho nên là chúng ta từ cái tư duy
this mindset that we begin to seek out
đấy chúng ta mới khởi tâm
knowledgeable individuals without tiring of searching for them.   That
bậc tri thức không nhà mỏi nha.
's what you call practicing virtue.  Happiness lies in
Thế gọi là cái hạnh tu đấy. Hạnh là cần
tirelessly seeking out virtuous and knowledgeable people.
cầu bậc thiện tri thức không nhàm mỏi.
Fourth item.  Reflecting on the benefits
Đề mục thứ tư. Tư duy về các việc lợi đã
gained
được
from obeying virtuous teachers, I vow to
khi vâng thuận thiện tri thức để phát
obey virtuous teachers from now on
nguyện từ nay sẽ vâng thuận bậc thiện
.
tri thức.
Dear fellow disciples, Tâm Chiếu
À kính thưa quý đội hữu, ở đây Tâm Chiếu
Restaurant would like to share a little
ăn quán xin chia sẻ một chút
something: after Tâm Chiếu Restaurant developed the Bodhi
đó là khi mà Tâm Chiếu Hàn Quán a phát
mind, the first thing
bồ đề tâm xong ấy thì việc đầu tiên là
Tâm Chiếu Restaurant did was go to find a teacher.  I was looking for a
Tâm Chiếu quán đi tìm thầy đấy. Đi tìm
teacher, my dear friends. When Tam
thầy đấy các quý đợi hữu à lúc mà Tâm
Chieu Quan returned to the temple and made the Bodhisattva vow, he
Chiế Quán được về chùa phát tâm bồ đề là
only knew to make the vow according to what his master
chỉ biết phát tâm theo là sư phụ đến
told him to do on that day; he
ngày đấy cho phát tâm phát tâm chứ lúc
didn't understand anything at that time.  But once I've made the vow,
đấy chưa hiểu đâu. Nhưng mình phát tâm
and I know that when I go looking for a
rồi mà mình cũng biết là mình đi tìm
teacher, I want to see who the right teacher is to help
thầy là xem là ai là thầy để thành tựu
me achieve enlightenment, then my mind contains this kind of contemplation
cho mình ấy thì tâm chứa quán có một cái
.  That is when the mind, filled with insight,
như này này. Đó là khi tâm chứa quán mới
directs itself towards the master, and the master will be the one who
nguyện hướng tâm là sư phụ sẽ là người
becomes one's teacher.  Then, the
mà là sư phụ của mình. Thì thâm chiếu
monk called the
quán bạch sư phụ gọi điện hối gọi điện
master, urgently asking him to accept
là con bạch thầy là con xin thầy nhận
him as a disciple.  Since you are my teacher, I will
con làm đệ tử. Thầy là sư phụ của con
obey whatever you teach me.
thì thầy dạy cái gì con xin vâng lời.
Therefore, when reading this sutra,
Thế cho nên ở cái cái cái bài kinh này
why does the mind's contemplation bring
tâm chế quán tại sao đọc lại thấy hoan
such joy?  Because I feel like I belong
hỉ như thế? Vì mình cảm thấy mình có ở
here.  Therefore, here, the focus of our
trong này. Thế cho nên ở chỗ này tâm
meditation is to give our esteemed fellow practitioners
chớn quán để cho các quý đạo hữu chúng
the object of reflection on the
ta cái đề mục đó là tư duy về các lợi
benefits received from obeying
ích đã được hưởng khi vâng thuận thiện
virtuous teachers, and to make a vow to obey virtuous teachers from now on
tri thức để phát nguyện từ nay sẽ vâng
.
thuận bậc thiện tri thức.
We must make a vow of obedience and submission in order to
Đấy phải phát nguyện vâng thuận thì mình
receive the advice of the esteemed elders.
mới được các quý đại ý ạ.
Fifth item.
Đề mục thứ năm.
When you aspire to seek the skillful
Khởi tâm mong muốn nơi thiện xảo phương
means of a virtuous teacher, do not see
tiện của bậc thiện tri thức, chớ thấy
fault in their teachings.  Do not harbor ill-intentioned thoughts when
lỗi lầm. Không bị tâm nghi bất thiện khi
receiving guidance from a virtuous teacher.  That is,
được bậc thiện tri thức chỉ dạy. Tức là
when we practice the Bodhisattva path and
khi mà chúng ta hành bồ tát đạo, chúng
meet virtuous teachers,
ta gặp được bậc thiện tri thức thì chúng
we are not afflicted by unwholesome thoughts.
ta không bị những cái tâm bất thiện.
Many people are like this.  When worshipping Buddha,
Nhiều người là có như này này. Lễ Phật
defilements arise in the mind.  Dear friends,
thì trong tâm khởi cấu ế. Các quý đợi
Although this teacher taught me very
Tuy rằng cái người thầy này dạy mình rất
well, and I couldn't find anything
là tốt, mình tìm ra không thấy cái gì
bad about him, whenever I think about him,
xấu nhưng mình cứ nghĩ đến người ta là
I get negative thoughts and negative images
mình bị khởi tâm bất thiện, hình ảnh bất
.  That's an obstacle
thiện. Cái đấy là một cái chướng ngại
for me, isn't it?  So here,
cho mình có phải không? Cho nên ở đây là
we will begin with that kind of aspiration
mình sẽ khởi cái tâm mong nguyện như
.  When one encounters a virtuous and
thế. Khi gặp được bậc thiện hữu tri
knowledgeable person who uses skillful means to guide and
thức, dùng pháp phương tiện độ cho mình,
instruct them, one will not develop
chỉ dạy cho mình thì mình không bị khởi
unwholesome thoughts or doubts about these
những cái tâm bất thiện, tâm nghi về các
virtuous and knowledgeable people.  Therefore,
bậc thiện, hữu tri thức. Thế cho nên ở
this is called "do not be deceived."  A
đây gọi là chớ thấy nỗi lầm. Cái tâm
skeptical mind is one that sees even wise and virtuous people as making
nghi là ch là thấy bậc thiện tri thức
mistakes.  What gives rise to
cũng lỗi lầm. Cái mà khởi những cái bất
unwholesome actions is error.  Is that right
thiện là cái đấy là lỗi lầm. Có phải
?  Therefore, the scripture teaches very
không? Cho nên bài kinh dạy văn từ rất
accurate vocabulary.  Sixth item.  We express our gratitude to the Three Jewels and the
là chuẩn ạ. Đề mục thứ sáu. Tri ân tam
Sangha for continuing to preserve the
bảo chư tăng đã nối tiếp giữ gìn Phật
Dharma, enabling us to learn and understand it, and
pháp khiến chúng ta được học hiểu và
helping us to learn virtuous practices.  We need to
giúp chúng ta học được các hạnh. Cần cầu
tirelessly seek out virtuous teachers, obeying them and following
thiện tri thức không nhàm mỏi vâng thuận
their skillful means without seeing
của bậc thiện tri thức không thấy lỗi
fault.
lầm.
Dear fellow practitioners,
Kính thưa quý đạo hữu ở các cái đề mục
these headings help us recall the content of the lesson
này để chúng ta nhớ lại nội dung của bài
so that we can further increase
để cho chúng ta tăng trưởng thêm được
our understanding.  That means
cái sự hiểu biết của chúng ta. Tức là
we meditate so that we can remember the lesson and
chúng ta ngồi thiền để chúng ta nhớ bài
increase our understanding.
tăng thêm cái sự hiểu biết của chúng ta.
And in this article, there is a very
Còn ở trong bài này thì có một phần rất
important part: the benefits of
là quan trọng đó là những cái lợi ích
being close to wise and
khi chúng ta được thân cận bậc thiện tri
virtuous people.  So we should write this part
thức. Thì cái phần này chúng ta cũng nên
down so we can
viết ra để chúng ta
remember it.  That is, we write it down clearly,
nhớ. Tức là chúng ta viết hẳn ra chúng
remembering that it is the part where the virtuous person
ta nhớ đó là cái phần mà lúc thiện tài
immediately had the thought that it is through associating with
liền phát ý nghĩ rằng ấy do thân cận
virtuous people that one can bravely and diligently cultivate the
thiện chư thức mà có thể dũng mãnh siêng
ultimate path.  Being close to
tu nhất thiết chí đạo. Do thân cận thiện
virtuous and knowledgeable people can lead to a quicker birth.  These great
tri thức mà có thể mau xuất sanh. những
vows, made through close association with virtuous teachers,
đại nguyện do thân cận thiện tri thức mà
enable one to endure boundless suffering for the sake of all sentient beings, even for
có thể vì chúng sinh thọ vô biên khổ tận
future eons.  By associating closely with virtuous and knowledgeable people, one
kiếp vị lai. Do thân cận thiện tri thức
can wear the armor of great diligence.
mà có thể mặc áo giáp đại tinh tấn.
In a single moment, the Dharma teachings resonate
Trong một vi trần thuyết pháp tiếng vang
throughout the entire universe; through close association with
khắp pháp giới, do thân cận thiện tri
virtuous teachers, one can quickly reach all directions.  Because of close
thức mà có thể mau đến tất cả phương. Do
association with virtuous and knowledgeable people, one can cultivate the Bodhisattva path for all eternity, even within a single
thân cận thiện tri thức mà ở trong một
strand of hair.
sợi lông tu Bồ Tát hạnh tận vị lai kiếp.
Through close association with virtuous
Do thân cận thiện tri thức mà ở trong
teachers, in every moment one truly practices the Bodhisattva path, even in ignorance of the teachings, one abides in the state of
mỗi niệm thật hành Bồ Tát hạnh dốt giáo
omniscience.  Through close association with
an trụ bực nhất thiết trí. Do thân cận
virtuous and knowledgeable people, one can enter the
thiện tri thức mà có thể nhập những đạo
majestic, powerful, and self-possessed paths of all
trang nghiêm thần lực tự tại của tất cả
Buddhas.  By associating with virtuous and knowledgeable people, one
Như Lai. Do thân cận thiện tri thức mà
can frequently access all
có thể thường vào khắp các
realms of Dharma.  Because of close association with virtuous and
môn pháp giới. Do thân cận thiện tri
knowledgeable people, one's connection to the Dharma realm never
thức nên thường duyên pháp giới chưa
arises, yet one can travel throughout the ten directions of the universe
từng động xuất mà có thể qua khắp quốc
.  So, here
độ mườ phương. Thì cái chỗ này là chúng
we just
ta chỉ
read to see the enormous benefits
đọc để thấy được cái lợi ích to lớn
.  I understand some parts and not
thôi. Có phần hiểu có phần không hiểu
others.  Seeing such benefits,
nhá. Thì cứ thấy được lợi ích như thế
we are inspired to associate with
cho nên chúng ta phát tâm thân cận bậc
virtuous and knowledgeable people.  Therefore, dear fellow
thiện hữu tri thức. Thì kính thưa quý
practitioners, we sincerely hope that when we
đạo hữu thì rất là mong khi mà chúng ta
genuinely cultivate the Bodhi mind in
à phát tâm bồ đề được chân thật đến kiếp
this lifetime, we will also receive benefits.  It means
này thì cũng được lợi ích. Đó là tâm
our minds are broadened, and we are relieved of the
chúng ta được mở rộng ra, chúng ta bớt
suffering caused by our narrow-minded selfishness and
cái phiền não do cái sự ích kỷ hẹp hòi
our lack of enlightenment.  And in future lives,
của chúng ta. Và đến các kiếp vị lai thì
our path
con đường đi của chúng ta
will follow our aspirations.  Mostly it's according to one's
sẽ theo nguyện. Phần nhiều là theo
wishes, and the remaining
nguyện, còn lại thì dư sót là những cái
karmic consequences lessen the suffering.  For example,
nghiệp thôi thì nó đỡ khổ. Ví dụ như là
in many aspects of life, we
trong các phần của cuộc đời thì chúng ta
follow our aspirations, while the rest, according to our
theo nguyện là nhiều, còn lại theo
karma, is merely like the winds blowing
nghiệp thì nó chỉ là những cái gió thổi
or the storms we encounter
hoặc là những cái cơn bão cơn miếc này
along our path, which we are
trên đường đi của chúng ta mà chúng ta
strong enough to overcome.  That way,
đủ sức để chúng ta vượt được. Thì như
it will be happier.  If
vậy thì nó sẽ được hạnh phúc hơn. Là
we don't make vows, we will be
chúng ta không phát nguyện thì chúng ta
led astray by karma.
bị nghiệp nó dẫn dắt chúng ta đi. Chúng
We have to pay for our karma with great suffering.  As
ta phải trả nghiệp rất là đau khổ. Phật
Buddhists, we are mindful practitioners who contemplate
tử chúng ta là người đang chánh niệm tư
the law of karma and its consequences.  Before
duy về tội phúc nhân quả. Cái lúc trước
we knew about Buddhism,
chúng ta chưa biết đến Phật pháp thì
we might have said that our suffering was a
chúng ta có thể nói là cái khổ của mình
gift or punishment from God
do ông trời ông ấy ban cho hay ông trừng
.  But now that we have practiced spiritual cultivation,
phạt. Nhưng bây giờ chúng ta có tu rồi,
we understand that all happiness and suffering are
chúng ta biết rồi, tất cả sướng khổ là
due to the seeds we have sown in the past,
do chính chúng ta đã gieo nhân từ trước
and now we must reap the fruits of suffering or
đến bây giờ phải hái quả khổ hoặc là
enjoy the fruits of blessings.  Therefore,
được hưởng cái quả phước. Thế vì thế cho
we can see that if we follow our wishes and
nên chúng ta thấy là cứ theo nguyện mà
do good deeds, our
làm việc thiện thì đương nhiên là cuộc
lives will naturally be more peaceful and joyful.  And we
đời sẽ được an vui hơn nhé. Và chúng ta
dedicate this merit
xin a hồi hướng cái công đức lành này
to all the deities in
đến cho tất cả các vị chư thiên à trên
the heavens where they reside.  All
các tầng trời chư thiên cư địa. Các qu
celestial beings, gods, spirits, and
vị chư thiên, chư thần, quỷ thần à tất
all sentient beings, all humans and non-
cả chúng sinh, tất cả chúng nhân và phi
humans, pray that the true Dharma may
nhân à nguyện cầu cho chánh pháp được
endure in the world for a long time.  All sentient beings
trụ lâu dài ở thế gian. chúng sinh thì
receive increased blessings, their present good wishes are
được tăng phước các cái thiện cầu hiện
quickly fulfilled, karmic conditions arise, they attain enlightenment in the
tại sớm được thành tựu được phát sinh
Buddha's teachings, they
nhân duyên được à giác ngộ Phật pháp
develop the Bodhi mind, they form Dharma companionship
được phát tâm bồ đề kết duyên pháp lữ
with us, supporting each other,
với chúng ta cùng trợ duyên cho nhau
becoming virtuous friends and knowledgeable individuals, receiving the protection and guidance of
cùng làm bậc thiện hữu tri thức cho nhau
Buddhas, Bodhisattvas, and holy monks
được chư Phật chư Bồ Tát chư thánh tăng
, and great virtuous friends, supporting and assisting us in our practice until the day we achieve supreme enlightenment. Until the day we fulfill that great vow: to liberate all sentient beings, to eradicate all afflictions, to
Nguyễn Độ, phiền não vô tận thệ nguyễn
learn all
đoạn, pháp môn vô lượng thệ nguyện học,
Dharma teachings, and to attain the supreme Buddha-path.  And
Phật đạo vô thượng thệ nguyện thành. Và
now, we are diligently practicing the
hiện tại thì chúng ta tinh tấn được
Bodhisattva path,
trong các cái công hạnh bồ đề à hội chỉ
spreading the Dharma throughout the
tam bảo truyền tải Phật pháp rộng khắp
world, and sowing the seeds of
thế gian và chúng ta gieo được những hạt
Bodhi, the qualities that allow the
giống bồ đề, những cái chất mà làm cho
Bodhi tree to grow.  That is the
cây bồ đề được tăng trưởng. Đó là công
merit of the six principles of harmony.  We dedicate this
đức của pháp lục hòa. À chúng con xin
merit and ask the Buddhas to bear
hồi hướng và chúng con xin chư Phật
witness and transfer the blessings according to
chứng minh chuyển phước báo đến theo lời
our prayers.
thình cầu của chúng con.
May
nguyện
this merit be
công đức này
directed towards all disciples and sentient beings, so that they may all
hướng a về khắp a tất cả ngi đệ tử và
choose to attain Buddhahood.
đều chọn thành Phật
[Music]
đạ
Then, I wish all esteemed fellow practitioners to diligently strive for
Rồi chúc các quý đạo hữu tinh tấn nguyện
all eternity, never
đời đời kiếp kiếp chúng ta không bao giờ
tiring in seeking to be close to
nhà mỏi trong việc cần cầu thân cận các
virtuous friends and knowledgeable people so that we
bậc thiện hữu tri thức để cho chúng ta
may practice the merits of the
được tu hành các cái công đức của các vị
Bodhisattvas who have cultivated to achieve supreme enlightenment
Bồ Tát đã tu hành để thành tựu vô thượng
.  Namo Buddha Shakyamuni.
bồ đề. Nam mô Phật Bổn Sư Thích Ca
Michael, the
Michael
golden chrysanthemum, though withered, will
Hoa cúc vàng quân từ dầu có héo cũng
not fall.  The flowers are also a noble yellow, and
không rơi mụy. Hoa cũng vàng thanh cao,
even when they wither, their color remains unchanged.
dầu có héo cũng không phải màu.
The club is also golden, the club is a hundred
Câu lạc bộ cũng vàng, câu lạc bộ trăm
years old, whether rich or poor, it will
thu, giàu có khó
not be discouraged, whether
cũng không nan lòng,
rich or poor, it
giàu có khó
will overcome any obstacle.   The
cũng sẽ vượt qua.
Chrysanthemum Club.  The Club of Joy.   Practice the
Câu lạc bộ cúc vàng. Câu lạc bộ an vui.
Buddhist path to harmony.  Golden Bow Club
Tu pháp Phật lùng hòa. Câu lạc bộ cung
.  The Club of Joy.  Buddhist practice and
vàng. Câu lạc bộ an vui. Tu pháp Phật
imperial duties.
lụng hoàng.
[Music]
[âm nhạc]
One, a flower stem standing on a pillar.  Two, a flower without a
Một, thân hoa đông trụ. Hai, khẩu hoa vô
fight.  Third, the idea of ​​the eastern flower is approved.  Fourth, the flower-cultivating realm
tranh. Ba, ý hoa đông duyệt. Bốn, giới
.  The year of the winter flower bloomed.  Six
hoa đông tu. Năm kiến hoa đông giải. Sáu
benefits of the East Light Flower.
lợi hoa đông quang.
Where there is harmony, there is peace and happiness.  Wherever
Ở đâu có lục hòa ở đó có an vui. Ở đâu
one practices the six harmonies, there is liberation.
tu lục hòa ở đó có giải thoát.
[Music] The
[âm nhạc]
Chrysanthemum Club, the Joyful Club.
Câu lạc bộ cúc vàng, câu lạc bộ an vui.
Practice the six harmonies of Buddhism.  The
Tu pháp Phật lục hòa. Câu lạc bộ cúc
Chrysanthemum Club, the Club of Joy.  Let's do our
vàng, câu lạc bộ an vui. Cùng nhau làm
duty together.  The Chrysanthemum Club, the Club of
phận sự. Câu lạc bộ cúc vàng, câu lạc bộ
Joy.  Let's practice self-cultivation together.
an vui. Cùng nhau tu tí tớ.
Develop the Bodhi mind.   To
Phát tâm bồ đề.
uphold the Three Jewels and spread the Buddha's teachings
Hộ trì Tam Bảo truyền tải Phật pháp rộng
throughout the world.
khắp thế gian.
[Music]
[âm nhạc]
Yellow chrysanthemums, the color of
Hoa cúc vàng quân từ màu hoa của giải
liberation.  The Chrysanthemum Club practices meditation to seek
thoát. Câu lạc bộ cúc vàng tu tập cầu
liberation and help others.  The
giải thoát giúp đỡ cho mọi người. Câu
Chrysanthemum Club, the Club of Joy.
lạc bộ cúc vàng, câu lạc bộ an vui. Tu
Cultivating the mind and seeking liberation: the gold offering club, the
tâm cầu giải thoát câu lạc bộ cúng vàng,
peace and joy club.  The club for offering gold, the
câu lạc bộ an vui. Câu lạc bộ cúng vàng,
club for peace and happiness.
câu lạc bộ an vui.
[Music] The
[âm nhạc]
Golden Chrysanthemum Club consists of people who are
Câu lạc bộ cúc vàng là những người phần
monks at Ba Pagoda and
từ tu tại chùa Ba và
always gather together to pray for the supreme
luôn cùng nhau tí tán để cầu vô thượng
enlightenment.   Let
đạo.
's trade together a little bit
Buôn cùng nhau tí t
[music]
[âm nhạc]
no harm
vô thương
[Applause]
[Vỗ tay]
Yellow chrysanthemums, soldiers from oil, even pigs
Hoa cúc vàng quân từ dầu cò heo cũng
don't fall, yellow chrysanthemums, pure gold,
không rơi hoa cúc vàng Vàng thanh cao
rich, even wilting isn't the color, the
giàu có héo cũng không phải màu
club is also gold, the club is a hundred years old.
câu lạc bộ cũng vàng câu lạc bộ trăm tu.
Even if wealth is difficult, it's not impossible; even if
cũng không nan lòng
wealth is difficult, it
giàu có khó
will be overcome.   The
cũng sẽ vượt qua.
Golden Chrysanthemum Club, the Club of Joy.
Câu lạc bộ cúc vàng câu lạc bộ an vui.
Buddhist practitioners seek harmony with the Golden Palace Club
Tu pháp Phật lùng hòa câu lạc bộ cung
.  The club for joyful practice of Buddhist teachings and searching for
vàng. Câu lạc bộ an vui tu pháp Phật
flowers.
lùng hoa.
[Music]
[âm nhạc]
A single flower standing on a pillar in winter.  Two flower-shaped guns without a
Một thân hoa đông trụ. Hai khẩu hoa vô
fight.  Third, the idea of ​​the eastern flower is approved.  Four realms of
tranh. Ba, ý hoa đông duyệt. Bốn giới
cultivation in the East.  The year of the winter flower bloomed.
hoa đông tu. Năm kiến hoa đông giải.
Six, benefit from the eastern light of the flower.
Sáu, lợi hoa đông quang.
Where there is harmony, there is peace and happiness.  Wherever
Ở đâu có lục hòa, ở đó có an vui. Ở đâu
one practices the six harmonies, there is liberation.
tu lục hòa, ở đó có giải thoát.
[Music] The
[âm nhạc]
Chrysanthemum Club, the Joyful Club.
Câu lạc bộ cúc vàng, câu lạc bộ an vui.
Practicing the Six Harmonious Principles of Buddhism, the
Tu pháp Phật lục hòa, câu lạc bộ cúc
Golden Chrysanthemum Club, the Club for Peace and Joy.  Together we fulfill our duties as members of the
vàng, câu lạc bộ an vui. Cùng nhau làm
Golden Chrysanthemum Club, the Club of Peace and
phận sự câu lạc bộ cúc vàng, câu lạc bộ
Joy.  Let's practice together and I'll
an vui. Cùng nhau tu tí tớ
develop the Bodhi mind.   To
phát tâm bồ đề.
uphold the Three Jewels and spread the Dharma
Hộ trì Tam Bảo, truyền tải Phật pháp
throughout the world.
rộng khắp thế gian.
[Music]
[âm nhạc]
Yellow chrysanthemums, the color of
Hoa cúc vàng quân từ màu hoa của giải
liberation.  The Chrysanthemum Club practices meditation to seek
thoát. Câu lạc bộ cúc vàng tu tập cầu
liberation and help others.  The
giải thoát giúp đỡ cho mọi người. Câu
Chrysanthemum Club, the Club of Joy.  Cultivate a virtuous
lạc bộ cúc vàng, câu lạc bộ an vui. Tu
mind to seek liberation.  The club is also
tâm cầu giải thoát. Câu lạc bộ cũng
golden, the club is joyful.  The club is also
vàng, câu lạc bộ an vui. Câu lạc bộ cũng
golden, the club is joyful.
vàng, câu lạc bộ an vui.
[Music] The
[âm nhạc]
Golden Chrysanthemum Club consists of people who are
Lạc bộ cúc vàng là những người phần từ
monks at Ba Pagoda and
tu tại chùa Ba và
always meditate together to seek the supreme
luôn cùng nhau tính tán để cầu vô thượng
path.   Always
đạo.
together, enjoying
Luôn cùng nhau tí tể
music,
[âm nhạc]
praying for peace and freedom.  aa
cầu vô thương đã. aa
[Applause]
[Vỗ tay]
also golden army from oil crane pig also does not
cũng vàng quân từ dầu cò heo cũng không
fall tears golden chrysanthemum Golden noble oil
rơi lụy hoa cúc vàng Vàng thanh cao dầu
even if withered is not the color
có héo cũng không phải màu
club also golden club hundred cultivation.
câu lạc bộ cũng vàng câu lạc bộ trăm tu.
Even if you're rich, you won't be discouraged;
cũng không nan lòng,
even if you face difficulties, you
dầu có khó
'll overcome them.   The
cũng sẽ vượt qua.
Chrysanthemum Club, the Club of Joy.   Practice the
Câu lạc bộ cúc vàng, câu lạc bộ an vui.
Buddhist path to harmony.  The Golden Club
Tu pháp Phật lùng hòa. Câu lạc bộ cung
, the Club of Joy.  The Dharma of the Buddha, Lung
vàng, câu lạc bộ an vui. Pháp Phật Lung
Hoa.
Hoa.
[Music]
[âm nhạc]
A single flower standing on a pillar in winter.  Two flower-shaped guns without a
Một thân hoa đông trụ. Hai khẩu hoa vô
fight.  Third, the idea of ​​the eastern flower is approved.  Four realms of
tranh. Ba, ý hoa đông duyệt. Bốn giới
cultivation in the East.  The year of the winter flower bloomed.
hoa đông tu. Năm kiến hoa đông giải.
Six, the profit of Dongguan flowers.
Sáu, lợi hoa đông quan.
Where there is harmony, there is peace and happiness.  Wherever
Ở đâu có lục hòa, ở đó có an vui. Ở đâu
one practices the six harmonies, there is liberation.
tu lục hòa, ở đó có giải thoát.
[Music] The
[âm nhạc]
Chrysanthemum Club, the Joyful Club.
Câu lạc bộ cúc vàng, câu lạc bộ an vui.
Buddhist practice, harmonious living,
Tu pháp Phật lụng hòa, câu lạc bộ cúc
golden chrysanthemum club, joyful club.  Working together to fulfill our
vàng, câu lạc bộ an vui. Cùng nhau làm
duties, the Golden Chrysanthemum Club, the Club of Peace and
phận sự, câu lạc bộ cúc vàng, câu lạc bộ
Joy.  Let's practice together and I'll
an vui. Cùng nhau tu tí tớ
develop the Bodhi mind.   To
phát tâm bồ đề.
uphold the Three Jewels and spread the teachings of Buddhism
Hộ trì Tam Bảo truyền tài Phật pháp rộng
throughout the world.
khắp thế gian.
[Music]
[âm nhạc]
Yellow chrysanthemums, the color of
Hoa cúc vàng quân từ màu hoa của giải
liberation.  The Chrysanthemum Club practices meditation to seek
thoát. Câu lạc bộ cúc vàng tu tập cầu
liberation and help others.  The
giải thoát giúp đỡ cho mọi người. Câu
Chrysanthemum Club, the Club of Joy.
lạc bộ cúc vàng, câu lạc bộ an vui. Tu
Cultivating the mind and seeking liberation: the Golden Chrysanthemum Club, the
tâm cầu giải thoát câu lạc bộ cúc vàng,
Club of Peace and Joy.  The Golden Bow Club, the
câu lạc bộ an vui. Câu lạc bộ cung vàng,
Club of Joy.
câu lạc bộ an vui.
[Music] The
[âm nhạc]
Golden Chrysanthemum Club members are monks
Cô lạc bộ cúc vàng là những người phần
from Ba Temple and
từ tu tại chùa Ba và
always meditate together to seek the supreme
luôn cùng nhau tính tán để cầu vô thượng
path,
đạo
always meditate together
luôn cùng nhau tinh t
to seek the ultimate truth.
để cầu vô thương
[Music]
[âm nhạc]